<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against heresy: or a preservative for Protestants against the poyson of Papists, Anabaptists, Arrians, Arminians, &amp;c. and their pestilent errours. Shewing the authors of those errours, their grounds and reasons, the time when and occasion how they did arise; with general answers to their arguments taken out of holy scripture and the ancient fathers. Written to stay the wandering and stablish the weak in these dangerous times of Apostasy. / By Richard Allen, M.A. sometime Fellow of Penbrooke [sic] Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Allen, Richard, b. 1604 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74986</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1045A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1168_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208803</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867726</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120048</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74986)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1168[2], 251:E1168[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against heresy: or a preservative for Protestants against the poyson of Papists, Anabaptists, Arrians, Arminians, &amp;c. and their pestilent errours. Shewing the authors of those errours, their grounds and reasons, the time when and occasion how they did arise; with general answers to their arguments taken out of holy scripture and the ancient fathers. Written to stay the wandering and stablish the weak in these dangerous times of Apostasy. / By Richard Allen, M.A. sometime Fellow of Penbrooke [sic] Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Allen, Richard, b. 1604 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock, and are to be sold by Nathaniel Brooks at the sign of the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imprimatur leaf signed and dated: James Cranford. March 28. 1648.</note>
                  <note>Thomason copy imperfect: significant show-through.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 28. 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian sects --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Arminianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE Againſt HERESY: OR A Preſervative for Proteſtants againſt the poyſon of Papiſts, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, Arrians, Arminians, &amp;c. and their peſtilent Errours.</p>
            <p>Shewing the Authors of thoſe Errours, their grounds and reaſons, the time when and occaſion how they did ariſe; with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Anſwers to their Arguments taken out of holy Scripture and the Ancient Fathers.</p>
            <p>Written to ſtay the wandering and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the weak in theſe dangerous times of Apoſtaſy.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD ALLEN, M. A. ſometime Fellow of <hi>Penbrooke</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 23.23.</hi>
               </bibl> Buy the Truth and ſell it not</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Nathaniel Brooks</hi> at the ſign of the Angel in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE Lords and Commons Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT. Grace and Peace be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DIfferences in the Church have always cauſed differences in the Commonwealth; and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in the Commonwelth do commonly widen thoſe differences in the Church. Differences in Religion did cauſe theſe unhappy and unnatural
<pb facs="tcp:120048:3"/> Wars; and theſe Wars have not ended but encreaſed them. For notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Solemn League and Covenant to extirpate all Popery, Hereſie, Schiſm, &amp;c. and in purſuance thereof your late pious Ordinance to ſtop their farther growth, beſides the excellent labours of many learned men, yet Hereſies are encreaſed above number, like the unruly waters, the more they are ſtopt, the more they rage and ſwell. And indeed Hereſie, Prophaneſs, Barbariſm, and Atheiſm it ſelf have always and in all places follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed war as cloſe as famine or peſtilence do; times of war and confuſion, being as fit times for the envious man to ſow his tares in, as times of peace, ſleep or ſecurity. And now for compoſing theſe differences; The Italians in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbial ſpeech uſe to ſay, that Hard to Hard never makes good ſtone-wall: Meaning, that in any difference, there muſt be ſome yeelding, or elſe there can never be any firm uniting. In matters of Religion, I have v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntured to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, my calling thereunto engaging me, with extream longings to ſee peace and truth ſettled amongſt us: Theſe poor labors, I humbly preſent unto
<pb facs="tcp:120048:3"/> your Honors, hoping your Honors will take in good part, what is intended to a good end, though perhaps it may come much ſhort of it; and accept the work though ſmall, ſeeing the ſmalleſt ſtone will help to repair the greateſt breach.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors humbly devoted <hi>RICHARD ALLEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:4"/>
            <p>monſter, that neither of the Swords yet could tame or cut off. But when I heard the moſt horrid Blaſphemies, and ſaw the monſtrous Hereſies that every day new-ſprang up, to the high diſhonor and displeaſure of Almighty God, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of his truth, ſaddening the hearts and dejecting the minds of his people: the enemy in mean ſpace riding in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph and treading down all before him: Setting aſide all doubts and fears, at laſt I finiſht and publiſht this ſmall book, partly inclined thereunto to yeeld ſome account of my late unpleaſing leiſure; but chiefly, for diſcharge of my duty, and a double engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that lay upon me: <hi>1.</hi> As a Chriſtian, being all bound, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle exhorts us, <hi>Jude 3. To contend earneſtly for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints. 2.</hi> As a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, which we are bound more ſpecially to defend, and not to give place to falſe teachers, <hi>No not for an hour that the truth of the Goſpel may continue,</hi> Gal. <hi>2.5.</hi> Beſides the ſolemn Covenant to extirpate all Hereſie, Schiſm, and Prophaneſs, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound doctrine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:5"/>
            <p>And now (right worſhipful) I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with it, ſuch as it is, being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged alſo thereunto by the many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors and kindneſſes I have received of you, whereof be pleaſed to tak this as an acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>I hope it may prove ſome help to diſcover the manifold ſleights and impoſtures of falſe Prophets and Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that are entered into the world, that privily bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them. And many follow their pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ways, but my prayers are always for you, that yee may ever eſcape their ſnares.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips much obliged Nephew,</hi> Richard Allen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:5"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE HEADS OR CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> OF the holy Scripture. <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Of the Bleſſed Trinity. <hi>Page 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> Of the Creation. <hi>Page 26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> Of Providence. <hi>Page 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Of the Fall of Man, and Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin. <hi>Page 35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Of Freewil. <hi>Page 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VII.</hi> Of the Perſon of Chriſt. <hi>Page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VIII.</hi> Of the Office of Chriſt. <hi>Page 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IX.</hi> Of the Death of Chriſt. <hi>Page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. X.</hi> Of the Reſurrection of Chriſt. <hi>Page 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> Of Predeſtination. <hi>Page 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XII.</hi> Of Vocation. <hi>Page 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XIII.</hi> Of Justification. <hi>Page 73</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:120048:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XIV.</hi> Of Sanctification. <hi>Page 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XV.</hi> Of the Moral Law. <hi>Page 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XVI.</hi> Of Good Works. <hi>Page 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XVII.</hi> Of Death and Burial. <hi>Page 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XVIII.</hi> Of the Reſurrection of the fleſh. <hi>Page 94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XIX.</hi> Of Glorification in Heaven. <hi>Page 96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XX.</hi> Of Hell. <hi>Page 98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXI.</hi> Of Purgatory. <hi>Page 99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXII.</hi> Of Images. <hi>Page 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXIII.</hi> Of the Church. <hi>Page 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXIV.</hi> Of the Sacraments. <hi>Page 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXV.</hi> Of Baptiſm. <hi>Page 119</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXVI.</hi> Of the Lords Supper. <hi>Page 126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXVII.</hi> Of Reformation. <hi>Page 134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XXVIII.</hi> Of Toleration. <hi>Page 143</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:6"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>GOD never wrought miracle to convince Atheiſm, becauſe his ordinary works convince it: <hi>For the Inviſible things of him, even his eternal power and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, are clearly ſeen and underſtood by the works of the Creation.</hi> Rom. <hi>1.20.</hi> And indeed never any people was heard of ſo barbarous, but did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg a God, and though otherwiſe, rude and voyd of all civility, yet did profeſs and practiſe ſome Religion. The very nature of man it ſelf ſo far abhors direct Atheiſm, that the Heathen made them Gods of wood and ſtone rather then have none at all, and gave Divine Honours, not to men only like themſelves, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to baſe and vile creatures, rather then be without a Religion. The Devil then not able to root up this perſwaſion of a Deity, ſo deeply and ſtrongly faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:120048:7"/> in the hearts of all men by nature; from Atheiſm he turned to Heatheniſm, from denying to multiplying the heaven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Deity, and with a multitude of falſe Gods abuſed the world almoſt <hi>4000.</hi> years. But When the fulneſs of time was come, God ſent his Son, a light to lighten the Gentiles, who with the beams of his glorious truth ſo ſcattered this u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal fog of Paganiſm, that thoſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanities were ſhortly diſcovered, mens conſciences convinced of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer groſs ignorance, and turned from dead Idols to ſerve the living God. And now this old Serpent is put to a new ſhift, which the Father of lies was not long to ſeek of, but driven from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm, betakes himſelf to Hereſie, for the worſhip of falſe Gods, ſetting up falſe worſhips of the true God, wherein he mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied ſo exceedingly, that now there are as many falſe worſhips, as before were falſe Gods. To trace this crooke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Serpent through all his turnings and windings, from the primitive times to this preſent, to obſerve the ſubtile ways and methods he hath uſed, to note by what ſteps and degrees he hath from time to time inſinuated himſelf into the
<pb facs="tcp:120048:7"/> very boſom of the Church, ſpreading this deadly poyſon over all its Members, and every point of Doctrine ſo, that the true Religion at this day lays gaſping and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring for life, is a work too great for ſo ſmall a volum. The firſt Instrument he found fit for this purpoſe was <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> of whom we read <hi>Acts 8.</hi> how he bewitched the people of <hi>Samaria.</hi> This Sorcerer is the Father of all Hereticks, and his Hereſie the curſed womb, from whence ſprang that numerous brood, that now covers the face of the earth, and hath raiſed the devil a mighty Kingdom. At this day it is divided (though not againſt it ſelf) in two main provinces, the <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt</hi> the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian;</hi> of the one the <hi>Turk</hi> is <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy,</hi> of the other the <hi>Pope</hi> is <hi>Vicar:</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe two <hi>Generaliſſimoes</hi> all thoſe enemies of Chriſt are liſted, both the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of his Perſon, and the enemies of his Office; among whom, though there be a ſeeming difference, yet indeed there is a ſecret league; like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, their heads look contrary ways, yet they are all Foxes, and joyned together by the tails. Theſe are the Foxes that ſpoyl the Lords Vineyard, and do more
<pb facs="tcp:120048:8"/> hurt by ſecret fraud, then the wild Boar by open force. <hi>Baalam</hi> a falſe Prophet, did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> more hurt then the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morites</hi> with all their Armies: And that Heretick <hi>Arrius</hi> did the Chriſtian Church more hurt then the Savage Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours did with all their Legions. No marvell then we are ſo often warned in holy Scripture to beware of theſe Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and falſe teachers, becauſe they creep in unawares. <hi>Jude 4.</hi> They bring in their Hereſies privily, and inſinuate themſelves with fained words. <hi>1 Pet. 2.1, 3.</hi> They have a form of godlineſs. <hi>2 Tim. 3.5.</hi> And with their fair outſides get within us, ſurpriſe, and lead us cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. And therefore we had need be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wary, and never more need then now; for Seducers wax worſe and worſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and being deceived. <hi>2 Tim. 4.</hi> They compaſs Sea and Land, they fill Town and Country; and not only creep into houſes, but up into high places, ſo bold they are grown. <hi>Now as Iannes and Iambres withſtood Moſes, ſo do theſe reſiſt the truth; men of corrupt minds, of no judgment concerning the Faith. 2</hi> Tim. <hi>3.8.</hi> But that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no further, here are diſcovered
<pb facs="tcp:120048:8"/> their Errours, that being ſeen, they may be ſhun'd and avoided. And though here be not diſcovered all, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible, yet here are, if I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake not, the principal, whereunto the rest are but acceſſory. The end of this ſmall work is to furniſh the weaker ſort, with general anſwers out of Gods own Word to the Arguments of the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and with plain Reaſons, if not ſufficient to defeat the enemy, yet enough I hope to defend themſelves; that they may be provided for them, whenſoever they be encountred by them, leſt being unprepared, at unawares they <hi>be led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the Errour of the wicked. 2</hi> Pet. <hi>3.17.</hi> Theſe are the firſt fruits of a larger harveſt, if it be accepted, being but a handful taken out of a heap.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:120048:9"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Cranford.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 28. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120048:9"/>
            <head>AN ANTIDOTE Againſt HERESIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the holy Scriptures.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament are the very Word of God,<note place="margin">Truth.</note> written by holy men as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt, and contain all things that are neceſſary to be known, or beleeved, to eternal ſalvation, being ſufficient of themſelves to inſtruct the Church or people of God thereunto. By holy Scripture we underſtand only thoſe books that were anciently accounted,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120048:10"/> and are now received by the Church of <hi>England</hi> for Canonical.</p>
               <p>Adverſaries and Errours<note place="margin">Errours.</note> that oppoſe this truth are many; but may all be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to theſe three heads. 1. Are thoſe that enlarge the Canon of holy Scripture, adding many things to it that are not of it. 2. Are thoſe that diminiſh the ſame, denying ſome parts, and taking ſome books from it. 3. There be thoſe that refuſe and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect the whole, debaſing and deſpiſing the Authority of the holy Scriptures, and eſteeming no better of them then of humane writings.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of this latter ſort were anciently <hi>Simon Magus, Montanus,</hi> and ſuch deceivers; and they are followed at this day by the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who call the written Word a dead letter, and ground their new doctrines upon reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, dreams and viſions, whereunto they give ſuch credit that at <hi>Sangal,</hi> a Town of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> one of them cut of his brothers head, pretending a revelation or command from heaven ſo to do: <hi>Sleidan Comment. l.</hi> 6. By this art <hi>Mahomet</hi> brought his damnable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in credit with the world; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the falling ſickneſs, he pretended
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120048:10"/> it was a trance wherein he received re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m heaven; and by the ſame art <hi>Muncer, Becold, Cnipperdolling,</hi> and other falſe Prophets of the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> ſeduced a world of poor miſerable people to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. The Papiſts ſay the Scriptures are of no more credit and authority then meer Fables, without the Teſtimony and approbation of the Church; and take them quite away from the reading of Lay-people as dangerous and hurtful: and have burnt not only the books of Scripture, but bodies of men too, for having them in a known tongue; ſuch bitter enemies they are to the Word of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There be others that deny not the whole, but diminiſh only the Canon of holy Scripture, refuſing ſome parts and rejecting ſome books: 1. The whole New-Teſtament, as the Jews do. Or 2. all the Old Teſtament, as the new Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines do, who affirm it is abrogated: the Socinians, who ſay it is unneceſſary, and may well be ſpared.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And there be others that enlarge the Canon of holy Scripture, adding many things to it, that are not of it; ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120048:11"/> the Papiſts do; not only traditions or unwritten verities, as they call them, but fabulous legends alſo and written lyes, upon a pretence of want and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the Scriptures, as not containing all truths neceſſary to ſalvation; nor ſufficient to inſtruct us thereunto, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſupply of Apochryphal books, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and divers humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>The Scriptures are the only touchſtone to try and diſcern Truth from Error by; and are called a Teſtament, becauſe they are <hi>teſtis mentis,</hi> the witneſs of Gods moſt holy will; againſt all adverſaries then, and their errours, we affirm;</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, that the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament are the very Word of God; of ſufficient authority and credit without the Church, or any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane teſtimony, to eſtabliſh any point of doctrine and decide any controverſie of Religion. For ſuch as the authority of the author of any writing is, ſuch is the authority of the writing it ſelf; but God is the Author of holy Scripture, therefore the Scriptures are of divine authority, of credit ſufficient in and of themſelves to be beleeved, without the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120048:11"/> teſtimony or approbation of any man or men. If the Scriptures be the Word of God, then who dares deny their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, refuſe what they command, or do what they forbid? But the Scriptures are the Word of God. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, The pen-men, that wrote them, were called and ſent of God; they were aſſiſted of God, confirming their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine with mighty ſigns and wonders, beyond any humane power or skill: and they were inſpired of God, teaching and writing, though themſelves ſimple and unlearned, moſt high and divine myſteries, above the reach of any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wit, and ſuch as the very Angels of Heaven deſired to look into.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The doctrine, or matter that is written, is, 1. Heavenly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine about heavenly and divine things. 2. It is moſt certain and true, all things that were foretold, moſt certainly came to paſs; and though they were written in ſeveral places, ages, and times, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons, of ſeveral arguments, yet all the books of holy Scripture, from the beginning to the end, do moſt ſweetly accord or agree together, as the dictates of one and the ſame Spirit of truth.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:120048:12"/>
               <p>Thirdly, The effects of this heavenly doctrine are divine and wonderful, as never any writings in the world did produce the like; For though it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to humane reaſon, and moſt croſs to our natural luſts and affections, yet it works and wins ſo upon men both powerfully and ſweetly, that it wooes and weans men, not only from the world, but alſo from themſelves; It diſcerns the thoughts, comforts the heart, enlightens the mind, convinceth the conſcience, and makes ſuch a change in the whole man that it makes him a new man, transforming and conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to the image of God in true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, all moſt ſure arguments of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It hath made a thorough conqueſt of the whole world, by the endeavors of very weak and ſilly men, bringing mighty Nations in obedience unto Chriſt, maugre all oppoſition that could be made againſt it, a plain demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that it is the Word of God and not of man; and it hath continued and been preſerved even to admiration, though a world of counſels have been taken, and attempts made to deſtroy it.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:120048:12"/>
               <p>Fifthly, The teſtimony of the Church in its due place is to be eſteemed as not a little moving; the conſent and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtians in all ages, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the ſufferings of holy Martyrs in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The teſtimony of the Holy Ghoſt to our hearts and conſciences puts all out of doubt: this doth not only perſwade, but moſt certainly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us that the Scriptures are the Word of God; it imprints a firm belief of it in our hearts, called the <hi>ſealing of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Eph.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The holy Scriptures give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of themſelves: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>All the Scripture is given by inspiration of God.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And the Prophets always deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their meſſage, with, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, The Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Scriptures then are of ſupream and ſoveraign authority; above the Church and greater then the Church by ſo much as the authority of God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the authority of men. The Scriptures, for the matter or ſubſtance,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120048:13"/> were before the Church, even that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſeed whereof the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch ſprang and grew, and is ſtill the ground where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſtands, the pillar whereby it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. The pillar and ground of the Church is the Scripture: <hi>Irenaeus</hi> l. 3. <hi>cont. Haer. c.</hi> 11. The authority of him that ſpake it, is ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it: <hi>Theodor. in Ezek. c.</hi> 34. The Scripture is to be judg in all matters of concroverſie: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law and to the Testimony.</hi> Joh. 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures for they teſtifie of me.</hi> Acts 17.11. The men of <hi>Berea</hi> ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed dayly the Scriptures, whether thoſe things were ſo as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, The Old Teſtament is not abrogated, or grown unprofitable; but together with the New is ſtill neceſſary for our inſtruction. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>All Scripture</hi> (the Old Teſtament as well as the New) <hi>is profitable for inſtruction. Joh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>(i.)</hi> the Old Teſtament; for then there was no other. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpake many things out of the Old Teſtament to confirm the doctrine of the New, therefore it is of as great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:120048:13"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But <hi>the Law and the Prophets were until</hi> John, <hi>ſince that time the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is preached,</hi> Luk. 16.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> They were until <hi>John,</hi> and then not abrogated but ſwallowed up of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light; the Old Teſtament is the ſame Goſpel that is in the New; the ſame Spirit, ſame Chriſt; <hi>Chriſt yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, to day, and the ſame for ever,</hi> Heb. 13.8. Yeſterday under the Law, to day under the Goſpel, and the ſame ſtill. The Old and New Teſtament give mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual light and teſtimony one to another; the one foretelling thoſe things that the other teſtifies are really and truly come to paſs.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament are perfect and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient of themſelves, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther help or ſupply, to inſtruct us in the means of ſalvation. We are forbidden to add to, or diminiſh any thing from it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19. And if a part were ſo perfect that it needed no addition, how much more the whole? <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.7. <hi>The Law of the Lord is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, converting the ſoul.</hi> Joh. 20.31. <hi>Theſe things were written, that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving we might have life everlasting;</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:120048:14"/> and what can be deſired more? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.17. <hi>The Scriptures make us wiſe unto ſalvation: they make the man of God perfect.</hi> This perfection of the Scripture excludes tradition; For what ſhall be added to that which is perfect? or what ſupply needs to that which is ſufficient of it ſelf? Tradition is either written or unwritten: 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. Written Tradition is the Scripture it ſelf: Unwritten Tradition, if it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Scripture, is included in the ſame, and ſo to be received as the Scripture it ſelf: if it be againſt or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Scripture, it is to be reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the fruit of ſome lying ſpirit, and not the Spirit of God, for as much as that Spirit of truth cannot contradict the written Word, whereof himſelf was the Author.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Fourthly, In all neceſſary points of faith the Scriptures are plain and eaſie enough to be underſtood, ſo that the ſimple and unlearned may and ought to read them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23. <hi>The Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a lamp or candle, and the Law is light.</hi> Pſa. 19.7, 8. <hi>The teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, and giveth wiſdom unto the ſimple; the Commandment of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120048:14"/> Lord is pure and giveth light unto the eyes.</hi> Pſa. 119. <hi>Thy Word is a lanthorn unto my feet, and a light unto my paths.</hi> And if it be a light, it muſt needs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten others, and cannot be hid but only to them that are loſt; not that the Scriptures themſelves are hidden, dark, and obſcure, but <hi>the god of this world hath blinded Their eyes,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. The end of the Scriptures, is the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Church; <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things were written, were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning;</hi> and one neceſſary mean to attain this end is the perſpicuity and plainneſs of the Scripture; for if it were dark or doubtful, how ſhould it inſtruct us? In vain is it called a Light, if it be dark in it ſelf; and to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are we ſent to learn it, if it be ſo to us. The Scriptures are an inſtrument to beget Faith: <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. And the firſt ſtep or degree of faith is knowledg, which the Scriptures could not beget if they were dark, difficult or obſcure.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, there are many things in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles <hi>hard to be understood, which unlearned men wreſt to their own deſtruction,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.16.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:120048:15"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> If any thing be hard in one place, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is ſuch as the ignorance thereof will not hazard our ſalvation, or elſe it is explained and made eaſie in another place. And by unlearned men the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle underſtand not men wanting hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning, as the liberal arts and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, &amp;c. but men unlearned in the Scriptures themſelves, ſuch as moſt times the learned and wiſe men of the world are. For it is known, that men otherwiſe unlearned, ſimple a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, coming in humility, the fear of God and love of truth, uſing prayer, reading, comparing of Scriptures, &amp;c. have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto a ſufficient meaſure of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledg. For the Scriptures diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves by their own proper light, one place expounding and opening the meaning of another; <hi>Auguſt. de Doct. Chriſt.</hi> .l 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.9.24. all things are ſeen by the light, but light by it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Laſtly, Thoſe books that we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call <hi>Apocrypha</hi> are not of divine authority, becauſe they were not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Prophets or men divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, as the other Scriptures were, that are therefore called <hi>the Scriptures of the Prophets,</hi> Rom. 12.26. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120048:15"/> divides all Canonical Scripture into <hi>Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> Luk. 16.29. But none of thoſe books were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Moſes</hi> or any of the Prophets, nor dictated by the Spirit of God, but ſavour of a prophane and lying ſpirit, as containing matter and ſtories, both vain, fooliſh, and fabulous, very often contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting themſelves, and alſo the known Word of God; as in the books of <hi>Tobit</hi> and the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> the <hi>Stories of Bell and the Dragon,</hi> are ſpecially to be found.</p>
               <p>The Jews received none of thoſe books in their Canon: neither by any of the primitive Chriſtians or ancient Fathers were accounted for Canonical: and what account the learned Papiſts themſelves make of them, may appear by <hi>Arias Montanus,</hi> who in the front of his Bible hath theſe words: <hi>There be added in this Edition the books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Greek, which the Catholick Church, following the Canon of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, reckoneth amongst the Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:120048:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Bleſſed Trinity.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THere is but one living and true God everlaſting; and in the unity of this Godhead there be three perſons of one ſubſtance, power and eternity, the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>This one point of Chriſtian Religion is the very baſis or foundation of all the reſt; and if this be ſhaken, the reſt muſt needs totter and fall to the ground: and therefore the devil hath raiſed up ſuch furious adverſaries to oppugn it with ſtrange and monſtrous blaſphemies; as of old did <hi>Simon Magus, Cerinthus, Ebion, Manes,</hi> a Perſian, a man accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his name furious and mad, and ſuch like: at this day the adverſaries to this doctrine of the Trinity are all the enemies of Chriſt and his divinity, as the unbeleeving <hi>Jews,</hi> all <hi>Mahometans, Turks, Moors,</hi> and ſuch miſcreants; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians only ſuch as have ſuckt their principles from the ſchools of thoſe Infidels.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:120048:16"/>
               <p>They ſtand marſhalled all in two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments. 1. The firſt is of thoſe that deny all diſtinction of perſons in the Godhead, making the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt but ſeveral names only of one and the ſame perſon in regard of ſome diſtinct actions or offices. This He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie was commonly aſcribed to <hi>Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> but <hi>Noetus</hi> a diſciple of <hi>Montanus</hi> hatcht it, and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> layd the egg long before; at this day it is revived by one M. <hi>Erbury,</hi> a late Chaplain of the <hi>Army,</hi> who taught, <hi>That there is but one perſon in the Godhead, and when we read of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, we muſt not take them for ſo many diſtinct perſons, but only as ſo many appearances of God unto men.</hi> And truly if M. <hi>Erbury</hi> had been that Sorcerers own diſciple, he could not have deviſed a doctrine more like his, as it is recorded by St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> lib. de Haereſ. ad <hi>Quodvultdeum</hi> cap. 1.</p>
               <p>There be others that admit a diſtinction of theſe 3 perſons but deny the equality of them, <hi>That the Son and Holy Ghost are not God equal with the Father, of one ſubstance and eternity with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> This was the Hereſie of <hi>Arius,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:120048:17"/> whoſe chief undertaking was againſt the Son of God and his eternal generation; and of <hi>Macedonius</hi> who denyed the Godhead of the holy Ghoſt. They are both revived at this day among us: that of <hi>Macedonius</hi> by one M. <hi>Biddle,</hi> who not queſtioning the Godhead of the Son, a point, as he profeſſeth, wherein he is not yet ſo well reſolved, denies only the Godhead of the holy Ghoſt, granting no more but, <hi>that he is an excellent creature, and chief of all the miniſtring ſpirits.</hi> One M. <hi>Beſt,</hi> not fearing that fearful judgment that befel <hi>Arius,</hi> (who burſt aſunder in the midſt like <hi>Judas</hi> the traitor, that his bowels guſhed out) hath notwithſtanding revived his Hereſie, and in theſe times of general and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Apoſtacy hath found many favorors and followers. Now the fountain of all theſe impure waters was <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> an impious ſorcerer: and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit that conveyed them to our times almoſt was <hi>Mahomet,</hi> an impudent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtour: For about the year 630. or as others pleaſe 670. that vile and lewd <hi>Arabian</hi> began his curſed book called the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and therein amongſt a multitude of other impure follies, impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120048:17"/> fables, and lyes he raked alſo together &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to his barbarous followers all thoſe Hereſies and Blaſphemies againſt the Trinity: Out of this filthy puddle <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Servertus</hi> a Spaniard, a man better read in <hi>Mahomets</hi> curſed Law then in the holy Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, ſuckt his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie; about the year 1530. for denying the eternal Son of God he was burnt at <hi>Geneva;</hi> and out of his aſhes aroſe that monſter <hi>Socinus.</hi> But to paſs by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, the firſt Country that made defection from this truth was <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> a Country bordering upon the <hi>Turks,</hi> from whom they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this point of their Religion; for to gratifie or comply with thoſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous neighbours, they abjured their Faith in the holy Trinity about the year 1593. denying the Son and holy Ghoſt: the contagion of this peſt is now ſpread into moſt places of Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>The devil hath deviſed and uſed many ways and manifold ſleights to elude this ſacred truth, but all drive at this one end, even to ſpoil (if it were poſſible) our Saviour Chriſt of his Divinity, and ſo deſtroy at one blow the whole body of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:120048:18"/>
               <p>The Antidote we ſhall divide into three doſes or propoſitions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That there are three perſons in the eternal Godhead, &amp;c. <hi>ſc.</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</item>
                  <item>2. That the Son is God everlaſting, equal with the Father.</item>
                  <item>3. That the holy Ghoſt is God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, equal with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. That there are three perſons in the Godhead, &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>And God ſaid, let us make man in Our Image.</hi> Gen. 3.23. <hi>And the Lord God ſaid, behold the man is become as one of us.</hi> Iſa. 6.8. <hi>And I heard the voyce of the Lord, ſaying, whom ſhall I ſend, and who will go for us? [I]</hi> plainly expreſſing the unity of eſſence, and <hi>[<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s]</hi> the plurality of perſons. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.24. <hi>And the Lord rained upon Sodom and upon Gomorrah fire and brimstone, from the Lord out of heaven.</hi> Hoſea 1.6, 7. <hi>God ſaid unto them, I will ſave them by the Lord their God.</hi> So <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8, 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.2. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.7. —<hi>the Lord ſaid unto me thou art my ſon. Gen.</hi> 1.2. <hi>The Spirit of God moved upon the waters.</hi> Mat. 3.16, 17. &amp; 28.19. <hi>The Father, Son and Holy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120048:18"/> Ghoſt</hi> are plainly and diſtinctly named. So 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.7. <hi>There are three that hear record in heaven, the Father, the Word</hi> (that is the Son) <hi>and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee how this ſacred truth, which at the beginning was more obſcure, in every age grew clearer and clearer like the morning light till it came to perfect day; firſt a plurality of perſons is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated; then a Trinity is expreſly named; and laſtly a plain difference or diſtinction is made of divers perſons, one ſpeaking of or to the other, and both are called the <hi>Lord of hoſts</hi> and <hi>Lord God.</hi> So <hi>Iob.</hi> 8.17, 18. <hi>The witneſs of two men is true, I am one, &amp;c.</hi> plainly making his Father and himſelf two. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.32.37. <hi>There is another that beareth witneſs of me; ſc.</hi> the Father: and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16, 17. <hi>And he will ſend you another Comforter, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Spirit of truth.</hi> Here the word <hi>[another]</hi> puts a manifeſt and plain dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erence between the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; ſo that there is another and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother, <hi>(i)</hi> three diſtinct perſons in the Godhead, but not another and another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing, for one ſingle undivided eſſence is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommon to all three.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:120048:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26. <hi>The Comforter &amp;c. which cometh out from the Father.</hi> Joh. 16.28. <hi>I came out from the Father.</hi> Now by theſe emanations or comings out of the Son and Holy Ghoſt from the Father, it is evident, that they are diſtinct perſons from the Father, each of them having a true ſubſiſtence proper to himſelf. And yet theſe three perſons are but one eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; three in one and one in three; differing but not divided; ſeveral but not ſundered; many and yet one: all diſtinct for their perſons, all one for their nature, ſubſtance, or eſſence; according to that 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. —<hi>and theſe three are one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> In this text we are to underſtand not an unity of eſſence but of conſent or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; as it is more plainly expreſt <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>and theſe three agree in one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> In theſe two verſes the Apoſtle op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the heavenly and earthly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the teſtimony of men and the teſtimony of God. The earthly witneſs he calls the teſtimony of men in the plural number, becauſe they are three in number, and though they agree in one, yet they are not one, but three dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and diſtinct things. The heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:120048:19"/> witneſs he calls the teſtimony of God in the ſingular number, <hi>v.</hi> 9. knitting three in one, becauſe though they are three in number, yet they are but one in nature, three perſons in one ſubſtance or eſſence: and ſo three bear witneſs in heaven, and yet all is the teſtimony but of one God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Son is God everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa. Who ſhall declare his generation.</hi> Joh. 1.14, 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Joh. 4.9. <hi>The only begotten Son of the Father.</hi> He is not a Son by grace, either of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the Angels, or Adoption as the Saints are; for then he were neither the only Son, nor begotten; <hi>To which of the Angels ſaid he at any time thou art my ſon?</hi> Heb. 1.8. No: for though they are all the ſons of God by Creation, yet this is the only Son by generation and God hath no other. The Son of God then cannot be a creature (as wicked Arrians affirm) becauſe he is begotten; for if he were made, created or adopted, then he were not the begotten Son, nor the only Son, becauſe by creation and adoption God hath more ſons then one. Now begetting is always of the nature and ſubſtance of the parents; and ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120048:20"/> this Son is begotten of Gods own ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, therefore alſo called his <hi>Own Son, Rom.</hi> 8.32. And becauſe God is a moſt ſingle eſſence, that cannot be divided or communicate it ſelf by parts, therefore he hath not a part, as the ſons of men have, but the whole ſubſtance of his Father, and ſo muſt needs be one God with the Father. He muſt needs alſo be coequal, of the ſame power and majeſty; and coeternal too, everlaſting as the Father himſelf is everlaſting, becauſe being both but one ſubſtance or eſſence, they were never nor could be one without the other.</p>
               <p>He is called in Scripture expreſly God, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>The mighty God.</hi> Tit. 2.13. <hi>The great God.</hi> 1 Joh. 5.20. <hi>The true God.</hi> Rom. 9.5. <hi>God over all.</hi> Pſa. 40.7. Heb. 1.8. —<hi>to the Son he ſaith, thy Throne, O God, endureth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such works are aſcribed to him as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree only to God. 1. The work of Creation. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.3. All things were made by him. Of Preſervation. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. All things are upheld by him. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.2. Forgiveth ſins. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.28. giveth eternal life, which none but God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do: and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.19. whatſoever the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120048:20"/> doth, that the Son doth likewiſe.</p>
               <p>The eſſential attributes of God are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him; as 1. Omnipotency, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. Eternity, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.6. Omniſcience, <hi>John</hi> 21.17. He is equal with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>John</hi> 5.18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6.</p>
               <p>Divine worſhip is given to him, which is due only to God: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.7. <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him all ye Gods, Heb.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Let all the Angels of God worſhip him.</hi> Which were plain Idolatry, if he were a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and <hi>John</hi> 5.23. the ſame honor is due to the Son that is due to the Father, The Apoſtles profeſs themſelves the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Jeſus Chriſt, Rom. 1.1. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Jude</hi> 1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1. We are commanded to truſt in him. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.12. To beleeve in him as we do in God, <hi>John</hi> 14.1. and <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi> But <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5.7. it is, <hi>Curſed are all they that truſt in man, and make fleſh their arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord:</hi> It is apparent then, that the Son is God equal with the Father.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Holy Ghoſt is God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, one living and true God with the Father and the Son. For, firſt, he is called expreſly both Lord and God, 1
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120048:21"/> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.5. and 6.28. <hi>the mighty God, Iſai.</hi> 40.13, 18. and <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.9. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25, 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.12, 13. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. &amp; 6.19. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. where he is called the Lord our God, the Lord our maker. Our bodies are the temples of the living God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. and the temples of the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. Now if we were commanded to build him a temple of wood and ſtone, it were a clear proof of his Godhead, becauſe this ſervice is only due unto God; how much more, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves are called his temple. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cont. Maxim. Arian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Divine attributes are given to him. 1. <hi>Omniſcience.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Omnipreſence, Pſal.</hi> 136.7. <hi>Eternity, Heb.</hi> 9.14. But above all, that which God takes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as a peculiar mark to be known from all falſe Gods, even to foretel things to come, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 41.23. is aſcribed to the Holy Ghoſt. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Such works are aſcribed to him as are proper only to God. As of 1. Creation. <hi>Job</hi> 26.13. &amp; 33.4. Of Preſervation. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. Of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Sanctification, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>Tit.</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:120048:21"/> 3.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. Alſo he raiſeth the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. And therefore the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond general Councel held under <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> the great, condemned <hi>Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in theſe words: <hi>If he were created, how doth he create? How doth he ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie? How doth he give life? &amp;c. for theſe are not the works of a creature. but the peculiar works of the great and mighty God.</hi> Laſtly, The very name of Spirit ſheweth his nature; for as the Spirit of man is of the nature of man, ſo the Spirit of God is of the nature of God; not a part, as the ſpirit of man is a part of him, but the whole Godhead, for the Divine Eſſence is not compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of parts. And whereas he is called the Spirit of the Son as well as of the Father, and is ſaid to be ſent or come by and from them both; from hence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears clearly the eſſential Union that is between them, that all three are but one God.</p>
               <p>The Catholick Faith then is this; That we worſhip one God in Trinity, and Trinity in Unity, neither confounding the perſons, nor dividing the ſubſtance: The Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God, and yet they are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120048:22"/> not three Gods but one God: For the Godhead of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt are all one, the glory equal, the Majeſty co-eternal. In this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity none is afore or after other, none greater or leſs then other; and he that will be ſaved muſt thus think of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Athanaſ. Symb.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Creation.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>IN the beginning God created the Heaven and the earth, and all things therein, both viſible and inviſible. Man he formed of the duſt of the ground; not corrupt and ſinful, as now he is, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own likeneſs or image, in true holineſs and perfect happineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>There were anciently many <hi>Errours</hi> about the Creation that now we do not hear of; the Maſters whereof were <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus, Cerinthus, Marcion, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicheus,</hi> and divers others. At this day, firſt, the old <hi>Anthropians</hi> or <hi>Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphites</hi> are new riſen: they concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120048:22"/> groſly, becauſe it is ſaid, man was made after the likeneſs of God, that therefore God had a body in ſhape like mans body: <hi>Epiphanius</hi> imputes it to their rudeneſs, ſparing to call them <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> but rather <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi> So the <hi>Meſſalian Haereticks,</hi> of old, thought that God might be ſeen with bodily eyes, miſtaking that ſaying of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> This <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> is maintained at this day by thoſe that affirm, that <hi>Adam</hi> was created af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the likeneſs of God in perſonal ſhape, and that God hath a perſonal ſhape, the which he can make viſible when he pleaſe. <hi>Ofiander</hi> taught, that man was made like unto God by influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the divine ſubſtance; an <hi>Errour</hi> borrowed of the <hi>Manichees</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcillianiſts:</hi> For <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> taught, that the body of man was made of the ſubſtance of the Prince of darkneſs, but his foul was part of the Divine ſubſtance. From the ſame ſtock ſprang that doctrine of one E. <hi>Avery,</hi> who publiſhed in print, <hi>Anno</hi> 1647. That the reaſonable ſoul in all mankind is God himſelf. With theſe rank the <hi>Familiſts,</hi> who ſay, That <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:120048:23"/> was all that <hi>God</hi> was, and <hi>God</hi> all that <hi>Adam</hi> was. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> alſo have their <hi>Errours,</hi> concerning the Image of God in <hi>Adam,</hi> original righteouſneſs, the place of Paradiſe, tree of life, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>Man was made after that the heaven and earth were finiſht, as a creature par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of both; in his ſoul heavenly, in his body earthly: a little model of the whole Creation. And it is ſaid, he was created after the likeneſs or Image of God, not that the body of man is like God in ſhape and proportion; for God is a Spirit, and hath no body or bodily members, no viſible form or lineament, and therefore is called the inviſible God. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.15. But man is like God. 1. In the grace, majeſty, and comelineſs of his body, excelling the other creatures, and after a ſort reſembling the Divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. 2. In his ſoul; Becauſe 1. It is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal like God. 2. It is endued with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and will like God, and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Divine graces, as wiſdom, knowledg, righteouſneſs and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that theſe are the more ſpecial and principal parts of the Image of God in man, appears, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10.3. Man is like God in his dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120048:23"/> the other creatures given him in his firſt Creation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28. being in that regard a petty God to other creatures, as Magiſtrates are to other men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. Laſtly, The very name of Image doth clearly evince, that the ſoul of man is not God himſelf, nor any part of the Divine ſubſtance, becauſe nothing is the Image of it ſelf, or can be ſaid like it ſelf. And the ſouls of wicked men ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for ever in hell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. And therefore the ſoul of man is no part of the Divine ſubſtance, but an immortal nature created of nothing by the power of God, and breathed into the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Divine Providence.</head>
               <p>GOD having made the world of nothing, did not leave it to it ſelf,<note place="margin">Truth.</note> but doth ſtil by his Almighty power and wiſdom ſuſtain and govern the ſame; preſerving all things that are, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all things that are done freely, and according to his own good pleaſure; ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120048:24"/> that nothing is, or comes to paſs raſhly, or by chance, but according to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his heavenly will.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>Adverſaries to this truth are, 1. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts</hi> and <hi>Epicures</hi> that deny all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, holding, That all things were created, and are dayly acted by chance and fortune. 2. <hi>Stoicks</hi> and <hi>Stoical Patrons</hi> of fate and deſtiny, that have deviſed a certain chain of ſecond cauſes, wherewith they have tyed Gods hands, as it were, and not left him the liberty to change, alter or order things at his own will and pleaſure. 3. <hi>Familiſts</hi> hold, That all things are ruled and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by nature. 4. Some place many things in our own power and freewill, which they ſay are not ſubject to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. 5. Worldlings aſcribe all the good that befalls them to their own wiſdom and endeavours. 6. Divers imagine that Gods Providence doth not reach unto every ſmall and trifting mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, conceiving it not agreeable to his Majeſty and greatneſs, even as it is too low and baſe for a Prince to look into the affairs of his Kitchin.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>That there is a Divine Providence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ſeeing and over-ruling the whole
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120048:24"/> world, and all things therein, is clear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a God infinite in wiſdom and power, which were not ſo, if any thing came to paſs by chance or fortune, or could be done without him, or beſide his will and pleaſure. The whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures bear witneſs unto this truth; and in particular, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.3. <hi>The eyes of the Lord are in every place.</hi> Pſal. 113.6. <hi>He abaſeth himſelf to behold things done in heaven and earth.</hi> Pſal. 135.6. <hi>Whatſoever the Lord pleaſed, that did he in heaven and in earth, &amp;c.</hi> For Iſai. 43.13. <hi>If he work, who ſhall hinder it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, God doth order and diſpoſe all things freely according to his own good will and pleaſure, without the leaſt compulſion or reſtraint: and it pleaſeth God to do many things contrary to the courſe of nature, as when he cauſed the Sun to ſtand ſtill at <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and go back at <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, to ſhew that the order or courſe of nature is nothing elſe but a Law or Statute of his own making, that he can repeal, alter and change when he pleaſe; and that all ſecond cauſes are but ſeveral links of Divine Providence that depend one upon another, and all upon God.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:120048:25"/>2. Secondly, Gods Providence extends to all creatures, even the moſt baſe and vile, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.27. All creatures wait upon him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.9. The poor Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens as well as the ſtately Lions, the peaſant as well as the Prince, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1. <hi>God ſtands in the Congregation of Princes,</hi> Pſal. 113.6. <hi>He takes the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of the duſt, and poor out of the mire,</hi> Pſal. 146. <hi>He relieveth the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and looſeth the priſoner.</hi> Pſal. 33.13. <hi>The Lord beholds all the children of men, and conſiders all that dwell upon the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, To the moſt caſual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.33. <hi>The lot is caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lap, but the whole diſpoſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is from the Lord:</hi> and what more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual then lots?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, To the moſt trivial things, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29. An hair doth not fall from our heads without his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and what more trivial?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fifthly, Even wicked and ſinful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are ſubject to Divine Providence; ſo that ſin it ſelf is not committed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out or beſide his will, his moſt wiſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ordering and turning it beyond the purpoſe or intent of the ſinner to his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:120048:25"/> own glory and good of his people, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.28. His hand and Counſel fore-deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined whatſoever was done againſt Chriſt: So that God was an actor in the buſineſs as well as <hi>Judas,</hi> and yet God was juſt and righteous, <hi>Judas</hi> wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſinful, becauſe in all one thing which they both did, there was not all one cauſe or end for which they did it. <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 48. <hi>ad Vincent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But if God have ſuch a hand and ſtroke in ſinful actions, then he is the Authour of ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> God forbid; God doth not infuſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evil or malice into us, but in him we live and move, and ſuch as we are, ſuch we are moved by him, unleſs he pleaſe to alter and change our nature. The earth gives ſap to all trees, but that ſome bring forth evil fruit, the fault is not in the earth, but in the evil quality or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the trees. God is an actour in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inful actions, and yet is not the Authour of ſin for all that: God hates ſin, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if he were the Author, how then ſhall he be the Judg? How ſhall he take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.5, 6.</p>
               <p>All things, then, that are, or are done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the world, are ſubject to Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120048:26"/> both Angels and men; bruit creatures, and devils themſelves; all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of men, high and low; their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, life, liberty and eſtates; all their actions, both natural, and voluntary; good and bad; nothing ſo ſmall that is hid from his ſight; nothing ſo caſual, but he directs it; nothing ſo trivial, but he takes notice and diſpoſeth of it.</p>
               <p>Great are the works of the Lord, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that after a marvellous &amp; unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able manner, that is not done beſide his wil, that yet is done againſt his will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhould not be done if he did not ſuffer it; neither doth he ſuffer it againſt his will, but with his will; neither would he, being good, ſuffer evil to be done, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, being alſo Almighty, he were able to bring good out of evil. <hi>August. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid. cap.</hi> 100.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:120048:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the fall of man, and of Original ſin.</head>
               <p>OUR firſt Parents, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note> were created in a perfect and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate, both holy and happy, but through their own voluntary diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in eating the forbidden fruit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods command, they fell from the ſame, plunging themſelves, and all their poſterity, into the contrary eſtate of ſin and death; ſo that by, and ever ſince that unhappy fall, the Image of God is defaced in all mankind, every mothers ſon is conceived in ſin, and born a child of wrath.</p>
               <p>Some endeavouring to extenuate the ſin of <hi>Adam,</hi> and make it leſs, ſay, That it was only the intemperance of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and his followers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Original ſin, affirming, That <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned only to his own hurt, and nothing at al hurt his poſterity thereby, ſo that no man ſhall ever periſh in hell for <hi>Adams</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:120048:27"/> ſin: That ſin is derived from the firſt man by imitation or example only, not by generation or natural diſcent: That Infants derive no ſin from their Parents, and therefore need not to be baptized, in their ſteps tread the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> do not deny Original ſin, but yet extreamly leſſen it, and make nothing almoſt of it; and they ſay, that concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence or ſin remaining after Baptiſm, is not truly ſin, nor ſo called, becauſe it is properly ſin, but becauſe it cometh of, and enclineth unto ſin, or is the matter whereof ſin is more eaſily bred; ſo they have decreed it quite againſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, accurſing all that dare ſay the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>Theſe are the divels ſubtilties, by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and hiding the diſeaſe to make it incurable; but that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin was no ſmall offence, being an act of horrid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt God, will appear, if we do but open and diſſect the ſame, and ſee how many foul ſins that one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains within it. As, 1. Intolerable pride and ambition, for not content with the Image of God ſtampt upon him; he affected alſo to be equal unto God in Majeſty, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Ye ſhall be as Gods.</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:120048:27"/> 2. Unthankfulneſs for that variety and plenty of all other creatures freely given for their uſe. 3. Foul Apoſtaſy from God to the devil Gods enemy. 4. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, the ground of all the reſt in deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Promiſe and Commandment of God, giving credit to the devil, who charged God with untruth, malice and envy of their good. <hi>v.</hi> 4.5. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſin is not to be weighed by an apple, or meaſured by the exceſs of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural appetite.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 2. Original ſin is ſo called, becauſe it takes beginning from our very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, birth and conception, ſo that we are ſinners ſo ſoon as we are or begin to be; according to that confeſſion of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 51.7. <hi>I was ſhapen in wickednes, and in ſin hath my mother conceived me.</hi> This Original or birth-ſin, is propagated over all mankind, and that two ways according to the two parts of it, <hi>ſc.</hi> the guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, and the corruption of nature; the firſt is propagated by imputation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>By one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>By the offence of one judgment came upon all men to condemnation.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>By the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:120048:28"/> of one many be dead.</hi> For being all in <hi>Adams</hi> loins, we ſinned in him, even as <hi>Levi</hi> being in <hi>Abrahams</hi> loins payed tythes. &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.9 The ſecond comes by generation, (whereon the firſt by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation alſo is grounded:) For <hi>Adam</hi> was the common ſtock &amp; root of al mankind, and could not derive unto us who are the branches any better ſap or quality then he had himſelf; the ſtreams cannot be ſweet if the ſpring be bitter, or pure if that be unclean, <hi>Job</hi> 14.4. <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean? truly no man.</hi> This Original corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts 1. In a diſability and averſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all that is good. 2. In a prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all manner of evil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. <hi>et ſeq.</hi> The parts affected with it, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all the parts and powers of body and ſoul: the underſtanding darkned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. the conſcience benummed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.19. the will enthralled, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. affections diſordered, <hi>James</hi> 4.1, 2. all the members of the body made Inſtruments of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15. &amp; 6.19. And ſo it is ſaid of <hi>Adam</hi> (though himſelf were created in the Image of God; yet after his fall) that he <hi>begat a ſon in his own likeneſs,</hi> (i.) corrupt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120048:28"/> like himſelf, the Image of God being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.3. It is clear then, that there is original ſin, <hi>(i.)</hi> an haereditary guilt and corruption that comes to us from our parents by natural generation, both by plain teſtimonies of Scripture, and alſo by experience in Infants: For although they have not <hi>ſinned after the likeneſs of Adams tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom. 5.14. <hi>(i.)</hi> actually, yet ſeeing death, which is the puniſhment of ſin, hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon infants as well as men; it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that they are born in ſin, for where there is no ſin, there can be no puniſhment due. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>By one man ſin entered into the world, and death by ſin.</hi> Rom. 6.23. <hi>The wages of ſin is death.</hi> Epheſ. 2.1, 3. <hi>We are dead in ſin, and by nature children of wrath.</hi> John 3.3, 6. <hi>Except a man be born again he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God: For that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh.</hi> If we were not corrupted with ſin in the firſt birth, there would not be ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a ſecond: a man in his natural birth is nothing but fleſh, and that this natural corruption remains ſtil in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and is properly ſin, ſee <hi>Rom</hi> 7.14. <hi>et ſeq. Gal.</hi> 5.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:120048:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Freewill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>SInce this lamentable fall of our firſt parents and by means of the ſame, the nature of man is ſo wholy corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the whole race of mankind brought into that miſerable bondage under ſin, that no man is able, by any natural power in himſelf, to beleeve in God, or turn unto him, to will or think, much leſs do any thing that is good and acceptable in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>Adverſaries to this doctrine were of old certain Philoſophers, out of whoſe ſchools crept the doctrine of <hi>Freewill,</hi> taught firſt by <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the <hi>Anabaptists, Arminians, Socinians, Papiſts, &amp;c.</hi> who ſay; <hi>That</hi> natural men have a power and freedom of will to chooſe &amp; do thoſe things that God commands, and to omit or refuſe thoſe things that he forbids: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſay they, God gave his Law in vain; in vain alſo are all counſels, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, precepts, promiſes and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenings;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:120048:29"/> rewards and puniſhments: neither can a man be juſtly puniſht for not doing thoſe duties that are impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him, or he not able to perform. That our Freewil was not loſt in the fall, but only weakened, that we are but half dead, and have ſome life and power ſtill left in us to ſtir up our ſelves; that grace is only an help to weak nature: and the like.</p>
               <p>Although by the fal of our firſt parents,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> the Image of God was defaced and our nature corrupted, yet man remains ſtill a creature reaſonable and capable of grace, having the ſame parts and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that he had before, and in them ſome reliques of Gods image; in the underſtanding ſome light and knowledg of God, and ſome notions of good and evil: in the will a liberty in natural and civil actions, and in all things a freedom from compulſion. But there is a four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold eſtate or condition of man: 1. Of Creation. 2. Of Corruption. 3. Of Renovation. 4. Of Glorification. All the queſtion is about the ſecond, what power a man in this condition hath to convert himſelf or to do good; and it is reſolved, according to the Scriptures,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:120048:30"/> that man by nature hath no power at all to do good, or turn himſelf to God. For 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves; but our ſufficiency is of God.</hi> Phil. 2.13. <hi>It is God that worketh in you, both to will and to do, of his own good pleaſure.</hi> Eph. 2.1. We are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dead in ſin; as unable to turn our ſelves unto God as a dead man to raiſe himſelf to life. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. Saith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Without me ye can do nothing.</hi> Joh. 6.44. <hi>No man can come unto me, except the Father draw him.</hi> Joh. 6.29 <hi>This is the work of God, that ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 16.17. <hi>Fleſh and blood</hi> cannot <hi>reveal Chriſt unto us &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concil. Arauſic.</hi> cap. 19. If man could not retain, without the grace of God, what he had received; how ſhall he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, without the ſame, what he hath loſt. <hi>Ambroſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de vocat. gent.</hi> Never let a man truſt his own ſtrength, now it is broken, that could not ſupport him when it was ſound and freſh about him. <hi>Bern. de gra. &amp; lib. arb.</hi> It were better we had never b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en, then to be at the diſpoſing of our own will: It is our own will that makes us the devils ſlaves,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120048:30"/> not his power; it is Gods grace that makes us his ſervants, not our own will. More teſtimonies might be brought; but whom theſe few will not ſuffice, thouſands more will never ſatisfie; <hi>Cui pauca non ſufficiunt, plura non prode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Concil. Arauſic. <hi>cap.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But if it be ſo; God may ſeem unjuſt to require that of us in his Law, that we are not able to perform.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Not at all: for in our firſt Creation God gave us ſufficient abilities which we loſt by our own voluntary fault, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. <hi>God made man upright, but they have found out many inventions:</hi> It is not unreaſonable then or unjuſt with God to require his own of us again, though we have prodigally loſt or miſpent it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> If man hath no power in himſelf to do good; to what end then are exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, admonitions, precepts, promiſes, or any preaching?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> They are not in vain, but the means ordained of God to ſoften our hearts, and bend our wills to his Will. St <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>God worketh in us both the will and the deed,</hi> and yet ceaſeth not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort us unto both: Our Saviour invites
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120048:31"/> us often to come unto him, and yet faith, <hi>No man can come unto me except the Father draw him,</hi> Ioh. 6.44.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Chriſt his Perſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>IN this miſerable and forlorn plight, the merciful God left us not to our ſelves, hopeleſs and helpleſs, but ſent his Son to take our nature upon him, that being perfect God and perfect man, he might fully ſatisfie for our ſins and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem our ſouls from death and hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>The enemies of Chriſt are of two ſorts. 1. The enemies of his perſon. 2. The enemies of his office. Of the firſt ſort were <hi>Simon Magus, Cerinthus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, Samoſatenus, Arius, Neſtorius,</hi> and ſuch Monſters: whereof ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed his Divinity, others his Humanity; Some the purity of his conception, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the truth of it: ſome confounded the two Natures, denying their diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; others denying their union, divided the perſon, of one making two: ſome
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:120048:31"/> ſaid he took tne body, but not the ſoul of man; others that he took an aetherial or ſpiritual, not a true body, and ſuch like. They are ſeconded at this day by the unbeleeving <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and all <hi>Mahometans, Antitrinitarians, New-Arians, Anabaptiſts, Familiſts, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> particularly by Mr <hi>Paul Beſt</hi> and others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who deny the Divinity of Chriſt, affirming, <hi>That he was but a meer man:</hi> ſome fear not to ſay, <hi>He was a ſinful man:</hi> ſome, <hi>That he was God, but not from everlaſting: the Son of God, but not before his, incarnation: God by merit, office or excellency of gifts, not by nature and generation.</hi> The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>he brought his fleſh with him from heaven, and took it not of the Virgin.</hi> The <hi>Familists</hi> turn the Incarnation of Chriſt into an Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory; holding, <hi>That every one of their family is Chriſt, and the taking in of their belief is the Incarnation:</hi> Having diſcourſe once with one of them, he would not ſay, Chriſt came or was come, but is now come in the fleſh; <hi>Chriſt is now come in my fleſh,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and now I ſpeak, Chriſt ſpeaks to you.</hi> So alſo Mr <hi>Erbury, By fleſh,</hi> ſaith he,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120048:32"/> 
                  <hi>is not meant the humane nut are, but the coming of Chriſt is the manifeſtation of the Godhead in the fleſh of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>Againſt theſe helliſh Blaſphemies we oppoſe theſe heavenly Truths.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, That our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is very God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.6. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto us a child is born, &amp;c, the Mighty God, Rom.</hi> 9.5. <hi>of whom Chriſt came, who is God over all bleſſed for ever.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God manifeſt in the fleſh.</hi> Rom. 1.4. <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mightily to be the Son of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, Chriſt is very man, and had a true body, taking fleſh of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> therefore often called the ſon of man: And 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>The man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Iſa. 7.14. <hi>A Virgin ſhall conceive, and bear a Son.</hi> Mat. 1.20. <hi>She was found with child by the Holy Ghost.</hi> Gal. 4.4. <hi>He was made of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> 1 John 1.1. <hi>The Word of Life, which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, and our hands have handled:</hi> He had a true body then, his humanity was obvious enough to all the ſenſes.</p>
               <p>If Chriſt be not God, why do you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore him? It is plain Idolatry to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Chriſt if he be not God. <hi>Cyril. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exand.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:120048:32"/> Cont. Eunom.</hi> The ſecond <hi>Nicene</hi> Councel Charged <hi>Neſtorius</hi> with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, becauſe he affirmed Chriſt was a meer man, &amp; yet adored him. S. <hi>Paul</hi> condemns ſerving the creature. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.25. and yet profeſſeth himſelf <hi>Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 1.1. Therefore Chriſt is no meer creature (or man.) <hi>Ambroſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de fide ad Gratian, Auguſt. c.</hi> 7. <hi>Arrians,</hi> then, <hi>Socinians,</hi> Mr. <hi>Best,</hi> and the reſt that deny Chriſt to be God, and yet grant that he ought to be adored; what do they differ from <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> that worſhip the creature? <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.22.25. <hi>Profeſſing themſelves to be wiſe, they become fools, and change the Truth of God into a lye:</hi> This then is Argument enough againſt the <hi>Arrians, Socinians; &amp;c.</hi> to prove the diety of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe according to their own divinity he ought to be ſerved, worſhipped, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored.</p>
               <p>The Heathen that knew God, and yet glorified him not as God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. And the <hi>Arrians, Socinians, &amp;c.</hi> that glorifie Chriſt as God, and yet acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg him not for God, are a like vain in their imagination, and their fooliſh heart is darkned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:120048:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Chriſt his Office.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THe Office of Chriſt, being God and man, is to mediate between God and man and reconcile them together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: God, who is angry for ſin; and man, who is guilty of ſin. This Office is three-fold: For, 1. as a Prophet, he doth inſtruct his Church. 2. As a Prieſt, he makes ſatisfaction and interceſſion for it. 3. As a King, he gathers and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns it.</p>
               <p>Adverſaries are thoſe, that affirm. 1.<note place="margin">Errours.</note> That Chriſt is Mediator only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his divine nature: So <hi>Oſiander.</hi> 2. That he is Mediator in reſpect of his humane nature only: So <hi>Stancarus.</hi> And of this opinion are the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who moſt wickedly ſet up other Mediators alſo beſides Chriſt, even Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, whom they pray unto to intercede for them. But the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are enemies to every part of his Office. 1. To his Kingly Office, in that they make the Pope head of the Church. 2. To his Prieſtly Office,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:120048:33"/> in that they ſet up other Mediatours and Interceſſours beſides Chriſt, and other ſatisfaction for ſin beſides that which he hath made. 3. To his Prophetical Office, in ſubjecting his holy Word to the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church, &amp; Judgment of the Pope a ſinful man; and equalizing traditions, and humane inventions with the ſame.</p>
               <p>Againſt theſe <hi>Errours</hi> we teach,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> and are taught. 1. <hi>That there is but one God, and one Mediator between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. He maketh interceſſion for us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. The Saints do not hear us, or know our wants. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.16. <hi>Abraham is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of us, and Iſrael doth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg us.</hi> Eccleſ. 9.5. <hi>The dead know not any thing:</hi> Job 5.1. <hi>Call now, if there be any that will anſwer, and to which of the Saints wilt thou turn?</hi> If <hi>Paul</hi> were a Mediatour, then the reſt of his fellow Apoſtles were ſo too: and if there be many Mediatours, then S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſaying 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. doth not hold good, that there is but one Mediatour &amp;c. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cont. Epiſt. Parmen. cap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is Mediatour according to both natures, according to his humane, he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and dyed; by the power of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:120048:34"/> he overcame death, and roſe again: without his humane nature he could not ſuffer: without his Divine to give price and value to his ſufferings he had not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; therefore it is ſaid, <hi>God purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Church with his own blood,</hi> Acts 20.28. Both natures did work in this Office of Mediatourſhip, each of them doing his own proper work, and yet both together producing but one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Death of Christ.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THe Office of Chriſt, as Mediatour, conſiſts of three parts, whereof his Prieſthood is principal; and of his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that oblation he made of himſelf upon the Croſs, whereby as the only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſin, he pacified the wrath of God, and redeeming our ſouls from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal death, purchaſed for us the favou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God, and life everlaſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>Adverſaries to this truth, are, 1. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> who affirm, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:120048:34"/> Chriſt by his death did not ſatisfie for our ſins. 2. <hi>Papists,</hi> who ſay, That Chriſt by his death indeed ſatisfied for our ſins, and for the eternal puniſhment due unto us for them; but for the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhment we muſt ſatisfie out ſelves, either in this life, or elſe hereafter in purgatory. 3. <hi>Arminians</hi> affirm, That Chriſt dyed for all men, as well thoſe that periſh, as thoſe that are ſaved; for <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> as well as <hi>Abell</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> From whence 4. Another riſeth, That a man whom Chriſt dyed for may periſh.</p>
               <p>The death of Chriſt being the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and total ſum, as it were,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> of all his ſufferings, from his cradle to his grave, is therefore commonly taken for the whole ſatisfaction that he made unto God for our ſins. To the Adverſaries we ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, That Chriſt by his death did ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for our ſins. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.5, 8, 10. <hi>His ſoul was made an offering for ſin, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 20.28. —<hi>A ranſom for many.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7. <hi>A Sacrifice for us.</hi> Rom. 4.25. <hi>He was delivered to death for our ſins.</hi> And 5.10. <hi>We were reconciled by his death.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.24. <hi>He bare our ſins
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120048:35"/> in his own body on the tree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But <hi>Micah</hi> 7.18. God forgives ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <hi>becauſe he delights in mercy:</hi> If Chriſt ſatisfie for ſin, how is it mercy?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> Chriſts merits, and Gods mercy, ſtand and agree together very wel. Chriſt hath ſatisfied, and yet we are freely forgiven, becauſe God exacts nothing of us but of Chriſt: It is free to us, we payed nothing; and though Chriſt made ſatisfaction, yet ſtill our ſins are freely forgiven us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt himſelf, for whoſe ſake our ſins are forgiven us, was freely given us.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, Chriſt ſatisfied, not only for eternal, but temporal puniſhment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: For otherwiſe, 1. It could not ſtand with Chriſts all-ſufficient Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, (who <hi>trod the wine-preſs of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wrath alone, and none helped him, Iſai.</hi> 63.3.) if we muſt ſatisfie for ſome part our ſelves. 2. It cannot ſtand with Gods mercy, who forgives us freely for Chriſts ſake. 3. It cannot ſtand with his Juſtice, when the fault is forgiven in exact any puniſhment; but they confeſs Chriſt hath ſatisfied for the fault fully therefore in Juſtice there can be no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment left for us to undergo.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:120048:35"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, Chriſt dyed not for all, but only for the elect. <hi>Mat</hi> 1.21. <hi>He ſhall ſave his people.</hi> John 10.15. <hi>I lay down my life for the ſheep.</hi> And 17.9. <hi>I pray for them, I pray not for the world, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Fourthly, A man that Chriſt hath dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for can never periſh. <hi>John</hi> 10.15. <hi>And I give them eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5. <hi>They are kept the Power of God unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> and what is able to controll that power?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But Chriſt is a ranſom for all. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Dyed for every man.</hi> Heb. 2.9. <hi>For the whole world.</hi> 1 John 2.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> By world, is meant the world of Gods Elect: ſo it is taken, <hi>John</hi> 6.33. and <hi>John</hi> 17.9. for the reprobate only. By <hi>[all]</hi> underſtand, all ſorts and degrees of men, all Countries and Nations; not the whole multitude of mankind, but the amplitude of grace only. <hi>August. Tract.</hi> 45. in <hi>Joan. He ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him for us all.</hi> Rom. 8.32. For all, whom? for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect; as it follows, <hi>v.</hi> 33. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld. Cont. Donat.</hi> God was in Chriſt reconciling the world unto himself; and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:120048:36"/> the ſon of man came not to judg the world, but to ſave it; but the world is not reconciled unto God, nor ſaved, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by world ye underſtand the Church, which is both reconciled and ſaved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Id. Epist.</hi> 48. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. The whole world lyeth in wickedneſs, <hi>(i.)</hi> the tares that grow all the world over: And again, Chriſt is a propitiation for the ſins of the whole world, <hi>(i.)</hi> for the wheat that likewiſe grows all world over.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Reſurrection of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>CHRIST did truly riſe again from death, and took his body, fleſh and bones, and all things appertaining to the perfection of mans nature; wherewith he aſcended into Heaven, and there fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at Gods right hand, until he return again to judgment at the end of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>
                  <hi>David George,</hi> the Father of the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, affirmed, That Chriſts body was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into aſhes, and ſo roſe no more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:120048:36"/> as of old <hi>Apelles</hi> ſaid, It was reſolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the four Elements, whereof it was at firſt compounded. 2. The <hi>Swenkfel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> affirm, That it is quite layed aſide. 3. The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquitaries,</hi> That it is every where, even as his Godhead is every where. 4. There be at this day, who affirm, That it is in the Sun; an old he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of the <hi>Manichees</hi> and <hi>Seleucians,</hi> who affirmed, That Chriſt in his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion left his body in the Sun, taking their ground for it from <hi>Pſal. 19.5. He ſet his tabernacle in the Sun,</hi> (as they read.)</p>
               <p>It is no great matter to beleeve that Chriſt dyed, this the Jews, Heathen,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> and all wicked men beleeve: but the faith of Chriſtians is the Reſurrection of Chriſt, <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. This one point is the very lock and key of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion: For 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.14. <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen, then is our preaching vain, our faith is alſo vain, we are ſtill in our ſins.</hi> But <hi>Mark</hi> 16.6. —<hi>He is not here, he is riſen.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.4. <hi>He was ſeen of Cephas, then of the twelve, then of five hundred brethren at once. Acts</hi> 2.31. <hi>Neither did his fleſh ſee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Mark.</hi> 16.19. <hi>He was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120048:37"/> into Heaven, and ſate at the right hand of God. Acts</hi> 3.21. <hi>Whom the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens muſt receive until the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring all things.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. <hi>The Communion is a remembrance of his death, till his coming again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Our Saviour himſelf ſays, <hi>Behold I am with you always, even to the end of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> That is, according to his Godhead, grace and Spirit; for according to his manhood he is altogether abſent from us, and locally in heaven. So our Saviour ſays again, <hi>Me ye have not always, Mat.</hi> 26.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of Predeſtination.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>SEeing the benefits of Chriſts death reach not to all, but to a certain cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen number: now follows the Decree of Gods Predeſtination, chuſing ſome to life eternal, and rejecting others, leaving them in their ſins to be damned for the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:120048:37"/>
               <p>Adverſaries, to this truth, are 1.<note place="margin">Errours.</note> 
                  <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians,</hi> both old and new, that ſcoff at this doctrine, denying the ſame; as there are at this day that ſay, it is not ſutable to God, nor agreeable to his nature, to pick and chooſe thus among men; to chuſe ſome, and refuſe others is partial and unjuſt. 2. <hi>Libertines</hi> abuſe this doctrine, as of old the <hi>Predeſtinates</hi> did, to all looſeneſs, thinking, that now they are predeſtinated, it is no matter how they live, becauſe nothing can help or hinder their ſalvation. 3. <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> ſay, That Predeſtination ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth nothing elſe in holy Scripture but Gods decree and purpoſe, to ſave thoſe that ſhall beleeve and obey, and dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe that ſhall not, denying the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency of it. 4. Denying the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Predeſtination, affirm, That God doth elect none until they do beleeve. 5. And deny the certainty and ſtability of it, affirming, that it is changeable, ſo that the elect may become reprobates, and the reprobates elect. 6. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in this point are contrary to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, affirming, both that God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen freely of his meer grace, and yet hath not choſen us but upon foreſight of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:120048:38"/> our good works. <hi>Bellarm. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Gra. et lib. arb. c.</hi> 16. But the general opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion among them is, That the Kingdom of Heaven is prepared for them that are worthy of it, and deſerve it by their well doing: and that a man doth make himſelf eligible to life eternal by his good works.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> There is a Predeſtination, <hi>(i.)</hi> an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of ſome to eternal life, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of others to eternal deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22, 23. There are veſſels of wrath, fitted for deſtruction; veſſels of mercy prepared for glory. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>As many as were ordained to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life beleeved.</hi> Prov. 16.4. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelf, yea the wicked for the day of evil.</hi> Jude 4. <hi>Before of old ordained to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. August. De civit. dei. l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 1. There are two Cities or Societies of men, one predeſtinated to raign for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with God; the other to ſuffer eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal puniſhment with the Divel.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, Predeſtination, both electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reprobation is eternal, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. Before we are born, or have done good or evil. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. Before the foundation of the world. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4. Before the world began.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:120048:38"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, It is free and independent; there is no moving cauſe of election to life, in the perſons predeſtinate, either foreſight of faith or good works, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the will and good pleaſure of God. And although ſin be the cauſe of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, being an act of Gods Juſtice, yet of reprobation, being an act of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power, there is no cauſe but the good pleaſure of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. <hi>He hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardeneth.</hi> Epheſ. 1.5. <hi>We are choſen according to the good pleſure of his will.</hi> Verſe 7. <hi>According to the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of his grace.</hi> Verſe. 11. <hi>After the Councel of his own will.</hi> 2 Tim. 1.9. <hi>Not according to works, but according to his own purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There can be no other cauſe beſide the Wil of God, becauſe there is nothing before the Will of God, which is it ſelf the cauſe of all things that are. <hi>August.</hi> Faith and obedience are the effect of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and cannot be the cauſe, becauſe they follow after, and do not go before it. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>As many as were ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto eternal life beleeved.</hi> 1 John 4.19. <hi>We love God, becauſe he loved us firſt,</hi> Rom. 8.29.30. From Gods Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120048:39"/> proceeds Predeſtination, from Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination Calling, from Calling Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Faith, Obedience, &amp;c. To ſay then we are predeſtinate in reſpect of our faith or works, is not only to invert the words of the Apoſtle, and falſifie his doctrine, but even to alter the very courſe of nature, by ſetting the effect before the cauſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.12. Before they had done either good or evil, it is ſaid, <hi>Jacob have I loved, but Eſau have I hated.</hi> Was it the foreſight of their good or evil works to come that moved God hereunto? That the Apoſtle denies in theſe words, <hi>That the purpoſe of God according to election, might ſtand, not of works, but of him that calleth. August. lib. de Predeſt. c.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Fourthly, It is immutable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable; the elect can never periſh nor the reprobates be ſaved. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>The foundation of God remaineth ſure, having this ſeal, the Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> Luke 10.20. <hi>Their, names are written in the book of life.</hi> John 10.3. <hi>He calleth his ſheep by name.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5. <hi>They are kept by the power of God unto ſalvation.</hi> They can never fall away and periſh, <hi>for whom he did predeſtinate,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120048:39"/> them he alſo called, &amp;c.</hi> Affording them in due time all thoſe means that ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly bring them unto glory. If any man, making a fair ſhew of holineſs, fall away, it is no Argument that the elect may fall away, but that thoſe which fall away are not elect. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. <hi>They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would have continued with us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſee it plain now, that God hath made a difference between men, chuſing ſome, and refuſing others: <hi>Latet diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ratio, non latet ipſa diſcretio. Ambroſ. de Vocat. Gent.</hi> We ſee the effect, we cannot perceive the cauſe; the thing it ſelf is manifeſt, the reaſon of it is hidden, and ſecret to us; and yet, though it be unknown, we know it cannot be unjuſt, becauſe it is the good pleaſure of his will, who is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works. Doth any man yet complain? Hear the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20, 21. <hi>O man, who art thou that replieſt against God! Hath not the Potter power over the clay?</hi> Do not diſpute, but fear and admire with the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>O the depth of the riches of the wiſdom of God, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120048:40"/> ſearchable are his Judgments!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we are all by nature one maſs of corruption; one is choſen, another is left; God ſheweth mercy upon one, and not upon another: how can any man complain now, when all were alike corrupt and culpable, and no deſert in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? Will every man diſpoſe freely of his own, and ſhall not God? If any man be ſaved then, he hath nothing to glory of but the riches of Gods mercy; and he that is damned, hath nothing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of but the merit of his own ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Some call this a licentious doctrine, and ſay, it ought not to be publiſht, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it overthrows all endeavours unto holineſs, and makes men looſe in their lives, or drives them to deſpair.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> The preaching of Gods grace, for the comfort of the godly, muſt not be ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, becauſe the ungodly turn it into wantoneſs. But this doctrine may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and confirm many, it can ſtumble none: none can preſume, neither need any to deſpair, that will but conſider, that God hath ordained the means as well as the end. Some are ordained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life eternal, but <hi>without holineſs we ſhall never ſee God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. —This
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:120048:40"/> cannot make us ſlothful or careleſs, but more diligent and ſtudious of good works, that by ſuch evidences we may make our calling and election ſure; ſure unto our own conſciences, which before was ſure enough in Gods eternal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. Some be ordained to deſtruction, but yet none ſhall be damned but for ſin; this cannot make any careleſs, but more careful to fly ſin, and be ſtudious of good works, which are not the cauſe, but yet the way to ſalvation, which God hath prepared for us to walk in, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. And ſo long as God affords the means of ſalvation, offering Chriſt day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto us in his Word and Sacraments; no man that waits upon the means hath any cauſe to deſpair.</p>
               <p>But, doeſt thou find the ſigns of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in thy ſelf? praiſe God for them. Doeſt thou not find them in another? pray to God for him. Doeſt thou find them in thy ſelf? be thankful. Doeſt thou not find them in another? yet be charitable, and hope ſtill, that God, who cals at all hours, may have an hour yet for thy neighbor as he had for thee. Shun all curioſity, and let theſe be the uſes you make of this doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:120048:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of Vocation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>
                  <hi>AND whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called;</hi> not only outwardly, by the preaching of his holy Word, but inwardly alſo, and effectually by the operation of his holy Spirit, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully working with the Word, and winning their hearts to cleave u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to him inſeparably to ſalvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>This is the ſecond link of that golden chain of ſalvation, that divers Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, both of former and latter times, have laboured to break aſunder: They are of three ſorts. 1. Thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the outward Miniſtry of the Word, as vain and unprofitable: So the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Gaſpar Swenckfeldius,</hi> and his followers, who affirm, That men are called, and faith is given, not by means of the Word, but by illumination, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate working of the Spirit; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly intent upon Speculations and Revelations, they imagine, that God doth reveal his Will unto them in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120048:41"/> dreams and viſions. By this device many lewd impoſtours have riſen, and abuſed the world with their lies, as <hi>Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Muncer</hi> did; and in the primitive times <hi>Simon Magus, Cerinthus, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> with their harlots, who, under the name of viſions and dreams, did broach and vent their own monſtrous dotages. The groſſeſt <hi>Errours</hi> that are now in Popery, as Purgatory, &amp;c. were firſt founded and confirmed by viſions and dreams; and by the ſame means the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lyes, and ſpirit of <hi>Errour,</hi> hath prevailed ſo far in the Church, as we ſee at this day; ſuch ſtrange and monſtrous ways men preſently fall into; when once they depart from the light of Gods known Word.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond ſort there be, that do not indeed condemn the outward Miniſtry of the Word, but yet eſteem very meanly of preaching and expounding the ſame, thinking and affirming, That bare read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures to the people is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for edifying them unto ſalvation, and that much or frequent preaching is not only not neceſſary but hurtful: This opinion was (if it be not ſtill) very cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant with many, both Miniſters and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:120048:42"/> people, and was mightily confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their minds, not by the connivence only, but alſo ill example and practiſe of the Biſhops themſelves, who, as if preaching were no part of their office, or derogatory to their high dignity, did moſt of them moſt ſhamefully caſt it quite off, (though indeed it would have been their greateſt glory:) and therefore now God hath juſtly covered them with ſhame for it, and poured contempt upon them. 3. The laſt and worſt ſort are thoſe enemies of grace, and patrons of freewil, the <hi>Pelagians, Papiſts, Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, &amp;c.</hi> who, to maintain the pride of nature, deny the power of grace, and to make good their former doctrine of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wil, have brought theſe ſeconds into the field: <hi>Viz.</hi> 1. That the grace of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is nothing elſe but a moral ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or probable inclination of the will, (which the outward preaching of the Word m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y effect;) denying the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful operation of the Spirit inwardly working upon the ſame. 2. That ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient grace to beleeve, and be converted, is offered and given to all in the Goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preached, and that with a ſerious inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in God to ſave all, but the Reaſon,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120048:42"/> why one receiveth grace, another recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it not; one believeth, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, another is not, is only in mans freewil, in whoſe power it is to receive and obey, or refuſe and reſiſt the offers and operations of grace. 3. That grace when it is gotten may be utterly loſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, faith quite cut off; and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The outward voyce or preaching of the Word is not of force or efficacy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to beget faith in a man,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> and turn him unto God, without the inward working, teaching, and calling of the Holy Ghoſt. But yet for all that, ſince the word hath been committed to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the written Word and preaching thereof, is the only outward and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry means ordained of God, to beget faith in us, and bring us to the knowledg and obedience of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the Word of God.</hi> Acts 10.44. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt fell upon them that heard the Word.</hi> And this was the Scripture or written Word; <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf took the book of <hi>Eſaias,</hi> and preacht the Scripture. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.35. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> preacht the Scripture to the Eunuch. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.2. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned out of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:120048:43"/> Scriptures. It is evident that all Churches both Jewiſh and Chriſtian uſed always to preach and hear the Scriptures for their edification. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.26. &amp; 13.15. It is given <hi>Timothy</hi> as a commendation, that <hi>he knew the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. And it is called <hi>the Word of Grace. Rom.</hi> 10.8. <hi>The Word of Faith. Act.</hi> 20.32. becauſe it is a means to convey both unto us. In times paſt indeed God was pleaſed to make his Will known unto his Servants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and by them to the people, divers ways, and after divers manners; as by Dreams, Viſions, Oracles, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim and Thummim.</hi> But in theſe laſt days he hath ſpoken unto us by his Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. who coming from the boſom of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath revealed all his Fathers Will unto us, that now we need no more any new Revelations: and therefore as the Apoſtle ſays, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16, 19, 20. We do not follow <hi>deviſed fables,</hi> for we have <hi>a more ſure word of prophecy,</hi> whereunto we take heed, even <hi>a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Scripture,</hi> or written Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, We read indeed in times of perſecution, that the very children did beget their own Fathers unto Chriſt, by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120048:43"/> reading unto them a few plain Chapters out of the New Teſtament, God giving a bleſſing thereunto, when better means were not afforded; yet it is evident, that bare reading without preaching is not enough, neither can we expect a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God upon one without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when he hath afforded the means and liberty of both. The common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all, both Jews and Chriſtians, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it: who were not content with bare reading but <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.9. <hi>they read in the Law, and gave the ſenſe, cauſing the people to underſtand the reading. Acts</hi> 13.15. After the reading, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>a Word of Exhortation.</hi> And our bleſſed Saviour, the great Doctor of his Church, after he had read, cloſed the book, and then preacht, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16. For bare reading without preaching or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding, is as bad to moſt people as ſpeaking in an unknown tongue, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> accounts madneſs. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, The grace of Vocation is External or Internal; External in the outward preaching of the Goſpel; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal in the 1. Illumination, or enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening of the mind with the knowledg
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:120048:44"/> of God. 2. Renovation, Regeneration, and Converſion of the heart and will, by changing, turning and winning the ſame to cleave unto God by Faith. We ſay then,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, That the outward calling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the inward, is not ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; the preacher cannot give Faith and repentance, which are the Work of God, <hi>John</hi> 6.29. and the Gift of God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. It is not moral ſwaſion or force of Argument; it is not the enticing words of mans wiſdom can change or turn that ſtony heart that is in the midſt of every one of us: it is Gods Work, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. called a Creation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10. and therefore his peculiar work. <hi>John</hi> 6.44. <hi>None can come to me except the Father draw him,</hi> ſaith our Saviour. It is not in the power of mans will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in bondage to Satan, and the powers of darkneſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. to return and come unto God; but we are called and beleeve, <hi>according to the exceeding greatneſs of his power,</hi> and <hi>according to the working of his mighty power,</hi> Eph. 1.18. <hi>And our Faith ſtands not in mans wiſdom, but in the power of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.5.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:120048:44"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, This grace of inward Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Regeneration, is irreſiſtible, that a man cannot reſiſt the operation of it, becauſe the purpoſe and power of God is in it. <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>All that the Father gave me ſhall come unto me:</hi> Not that God offers any compulſion or violence to the will, for then it were not will; he draws us indeed, but with cords of love; moſt ſweetly wooing us, and yet ſo powerfully winning us, after a manner unſpeakable, that we cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, becauſe we cannot but yield; our nature being changed by his grace, and of unwilling made willing to obey.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, This inward calling is immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, becauſe it is <hi>according to Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> Rom. 8.28. and that is unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. <hi>The Gifts and Calling of God are without repentance.</hi> And ſo the Regenerate, thoſe that are effectually called can never fall wholly away again: For <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.4. <hi>God makes an everlaſting Covenant with them, and puts his fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Fourthly, This grace of inward Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is free (otherwiſe it were not grace) not gotten by any diligence and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:120048:45"/> endeavour, or given for any dignity or worthineſs in the perſon called, but free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to Gods good pleaſure: ſo that the reaſon why one man receiveth grace, another receiveth it not; one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves, another doth not; one is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, another is not; is not in man that willeth, but in God that worketh and diſpenſeth his grace according to his own pleaſure, opening the heart of one, and not of another. <hi>John</hi> 3.8. <hi>The wind bloweth where it liſteth, &amp;c. Even ſo is every man that is born of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Laſtly, It is proper and peculiar to Gods Elect. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Whom he did predeſtinate them he alſo called;</hi> and none elſe. Indeed, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are called that are not choſen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.14. but none effectually. There is a calling of nature, and a calling of grace; many are called by the voyce of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that never heard the Scriptures; many are invited by the Word, that are not won by the Spirit; have their minds enlightened too, and yet their hearts not opened or renewed. Many are called outwardly, that are not inwardly and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually: this is peculiar to Gods cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, who are called by his Spirit working
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:120048:45"/> in due ſeaſon; through grace they obey that calling; are freely juſtified; and at laſt moſt certainly glorified. The Elect are ſtill ſure of ſalvation, becauſe the links of this golden chain are ſo ſtrongly faſtened one within another according to Gods unchangeable purpoſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible power, that they can never be broken and undone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of Justification.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND whom he called,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note> 
                  <hi>them he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Juſtified;</hi> and we are Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or accounted righteous in the ſight of God, not for any works or worthineſs of our own, but for the only merits of Jeſus Chriſt, and by faith in him, our ſins being imputed unto him, and his Righteouſneſs unto us.</p>
               <p>Adverſaries to this Doctrine are the Papiſts,<note place="margin">Errours.</note> with their brethren the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts. The Anabaptiſts teach, That we are not juſtified by faith alone, but by the croſs and affliction. The Papiſts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:120048:46"/> 1. That we are not juſtified by faith only, but by faith and works toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and works in their account carry the greateſt ſtroke. 2. That we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith, not as an Inſtrument, but as a vertue meriting or deſerving, and ſo tis a part of that Righteouſneſs whereby we are juſtified before God. 3. That we are juſtified before God by a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs that is inherent in us; infuſed, not imputed. 4 <hi>Oſiander</hi> imagined, That we are ſubſtantially righteous in Chriſt, as well in Eſſence as in quality; and that the truly righteous do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend Chriſt by faith, but have him and his Righteouſneſs eſſentially derived unto them; ſo that in our Juſtification God conveying himſelf into us, maketh us a part of himſelf: So the Familiſts ſay, That every one of their family is Chriſt, godded with God, and deified. 5. Many Phariſaical Chriſtians there be that think to be juſtified by civil and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Righteouſneſs. 6. And certain Libertines, That taking no care of wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing think to be juſtified by faith alone, or a ſolitary faith. 7. A world of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal people regard neither faith nor works, and yet hope to be ſaved as well as the beſt.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:120048:46"/>
               <p>This point of Juſtification,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that is in Controverſie between us and the Papiſts, which they quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and therewith the whole Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, burying Chriſt again, that is riſen for our Juſtification: For if our works before or after Juſtification do merit grace and life by congruity or condigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then is Chriſt in vain, and become of no effect.</p>
               <p>To the Adverſaries we ſay; Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 1. That we are juſtified without works by faith alone; not that faith is or can be alone without good works, in reſpect of its Eſſence; but in the act of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation it is alone, as it is an Inſtrument of Juſtification. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 143.2. <hi>Enter not into judgment with thy ſervant, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> Iob 15.15. <hi>What is man that he ſhould be juſt, or he that is born of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that he ſhould be righteous.</hi> Rom. 3.20. <hi>By the works of the Law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified.</hi> Gal. 3.11. <hi>And that no man is juſtified by works, is evident For the juſt ſhall live by faith.</hi> Rom. 3.28. <hi>We conclude then, that a man is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified by faith without works.</hi> Good works indeed may juſtifie us before men
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:120048:47"/> as an evidence of our faith, and of this S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.24. <hi>Ye ſee then how by works a man is juſtified:</hi> But before God we are juſtified only by the perfect Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, applyed unto us by the hand of faith, wherein our own works have not the leaſt finger.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, we are juſtified by faith, not as the cauſe, but only as an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Juſtification; not as it is a vertue inherent in us, but as it goes forth, and apprehends and applies Chriſt unto us; not by the merit of faith, but by the merits of Chriſt applyed by faith; and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. <hi>The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God is by, faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all that believe:</hi> And v. 24. <hi>We are juſtified through the redemption that is in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And Phil. 3.9. The righteouſneſs whereby we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified before God, is called <hi>the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs that is through the Faith of Chriſt:</hi> and <hi>the Righteouſneſs by faith;</hi> and therefore when it is ſaid we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith, it notes the uſe or effect, not the merit or dignity of faith: For 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Christ is made unto us Righteouſneſs.</hi> And 2 Cor. 5.21. <hi>We are made the Righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:120048:47"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, There is a glorifying Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in the world to come; In this world a ſanctifying &amp; a juſtifying Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; that wherewith we ſhall be dothed in the world to come, is both perfect and inherent, that wherewith we are ſanctified in this life is inherent, but not perfect; that wherewith we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified is perfect, but not inherent. The Righteouſneſs whereby we are juſtified before God, is not inherent in us but in Chriſt; in us, not by inheſion, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, whereby we are juſtified, is not infuſed, but imputed to us, and accounted ours: So <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Abraham</hi> was iuſtified by a Righteouſneſs imputed or account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>We are made the Righteouſneſs of God in him;</hi> the Righteouſneſs of God, not ours; in him, not in us, <hi>Auguſt. Enchirid. cap.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, When we ſay we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith alone, we do not mean a faith that is alone, that is ſolitary with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good works, but a living faith, and a working faith; for a dead faith cannot juſtifie, and a living faith cannot be idle, but worketh by love, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.5. We are juſtified by faith alone, without works;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:120048:48"/> not that works are ſeparated from faith, or can be; but only excluded from the act of Juſtification.</p>
               <p>The parts of our Juſtification, are, 1. The imputation of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 2. Forgiveneſs of our ſins. The inward moving cauſe is Gods mercy: the outward is Chriſts merit. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal cauſe is the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſs; the inſtrumental faith, and faith without works; whereby works are excluded not from the nature of Faith, but from the act of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of Sanctification.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>WHom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified: Our glorification, which ſhall be finiſht and compleated in the life to come, is begun in this life; partly in regard of our condition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are made happy, and partly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our nature wherein we are made holy. We are made holy in our nature
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:120048:48"/> by the grace of Sanctification, which is the renewing of our whole nature (though not wholy in this life) accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the image of God in righteouſneſs and true holineſs.</p>
               <p>Adverſaries to this truth were, 1.<note place="margin">Errours.</note> 
                  <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> and his diſciples, who gave libertie to all looſeneſs and uncleanneſs, ſaying, That ſin defiled the body, but not the ſoul: and they are followed by the Libertines of our age, who ſcoff at all ſanctitie or holineſs of living: And if you obſerve you ſhall find, that holineſs of life is had in great eſteem and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence among all ſorts and ſects, among Papiſts and the very Turks themſelves, after their way; only it is in diſgrace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our common Proteſtants, who uſually deſpiſe and brand thoſe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious names, who are any way ſtrict and ſevere in their lives, endevoring to live in the fear of God. 2. Some Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, as the Adamites and Familiſts, ſay, that they re perfect and pure from all ſin, and that there are men living as perfect and pure as Chriſt was. So the Pelagians and Donatiſts of old; of latter time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Sect called <hi>Fratricelli</hi> affirmed, that a man might attain in this life to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120048:49"/> that perfection, to be without ſin; and he that is ſo, is freed from all ſubjection to mortal men, and had no more need of prayer, faſting, or ſuch exerciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of piety: Among theſe Perfectiſts we rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon alſo the Papiſts. 3. There be others ſo contrary to the Papiſts, who would have juſtifying righteouſneſs inherent in us, that theſe will have none at all, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, that Chriſt is the new creature, and all graces are in Chriſt as in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, none in us; upon which follow many other ſtrange doctrines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>Now we are juſtified by faith through the free grace of God, we ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after holineſs with the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: 1. That we may glorifie Gods name, who hath done ſo great things for us: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. Becauſe 2. it is the will of God. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3. Becauſe 3. it is the end of our election: <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. <hi>He hath choſen us that we ſhould be holy.</hi> 4. It is the end of our Redemption, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74. He hath ſaved us that we ſhould ſerve him. 5. It is the end of our calling: 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.7. <hi>God hath called us unto holineſs:</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Without holineſs we ſhall never ſee God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:120048:49"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, Though we ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour and follow after holineſs, yet we can never be perfect, or without ſin in this life. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us. James</hi> 3.2. <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.40. <hi>There is no man that ſinneth not. Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Who can ſay I am pure from my ſin. Eccleſ.</hi> 7.10. <hi>There is not a juſt man upon earth that doth good, and ſinneth not:</hi> as is evident by the confeſſions and examples of holy men of God. Noah, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.21. Abraham, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.2. Lot, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.33. David, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. Paul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. and Peter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed his Maſter Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. The Perfectiſts themſelves have enough in themſelves to convince them of their folly; as pride, envy, malice, &amp;c. being ſubject to ſickneſs, death, &amp;c. which are the wages of ſin, and therefore they are not without ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Our Saviour exhorts us to be <hi>perfect as our heavenly Father is perfect. Mat.</hi> 5,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> There is a pattern propoſed unto us to imitate and follow, not to match e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, or overtake, which cannot be:
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:120048:50"/> 
                  <hi>[As]</hi> noteth the quality, not equality.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God ſinneth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> The ſame Apoſtle ſays, <hi>If we ſay we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves.</hi> We ſin then, <hi>(i.)</hi> ſins of infirmity: and we do not ſin, <hi>(i.)</hi> we do not fall back in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſervice and dominion of ſin final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or totally. There is a perfection, 1. Of degrees, and ſtands oppoſed to imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. 2. Of parts, and ſtands oppoſed to hypocriſy. This latter we may have, <hi>(i.)</hi> be ſincere and upright, not the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>(i.)</hi> be free from all ſin, defect or imperfection. Many men in Scripture are called righteous, juſt, perfect, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were without all vice, but becauſe they had many vertues; <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nym:</hi> For otherwiſe <hi>Noah</hi> was drunk, <hi>David</hi> committed Adultery, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, The righteouſneſs whereby we are juſtified is inherent in Chriſt for us; that whereby we are ſanctified, is inherent in our ſelves from Chriſt; that is in us only by imputation; this alſo by infuſion and real Communication; by that we are freed from the guilt, by this from the pollution of ſin; that is done al at once, this by degrees. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. <hi>The
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:120048:50"/> inward man is renewed day by day.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Stir up the grace that is in thee.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Add to your faith ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, &amp;c. For if theſe things be in you, &amp;c.</hi> the Righteouſneſs then of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is ſubjectively in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Fourthly, Our Sanctification is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of our Juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10, 14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Laſtly, God doth ſee ſin in his deareſt Saints; as in the example of <hi>David;</hi> who alſo confeſſeth the ſame, was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, and prayed for pardon, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51. If God did not ſee ſin in him, how did he ſend <hi>Nathan</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove him for it; why did he puniſh him for it? Our Saviour teaches us to pray for pardon of ſins. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.12. The Apoſtle 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. to confeſs our ſins. And <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Peter</hi> wept bitterly for his ſin. We ought to ſorrow for ſin; and renew our ſouls dayly by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:120048:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the Moral Law.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>CHriſt hath delivered us from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and curſe of the Law, not from all obedience unto it, but that it ſtill remains a rule of life unto us.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>
                  <hi>Antinomians</hi> or <hi>Adverſaries</hi> to this truth (becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>We are not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, but under Grace, Rom.</hi> 6.14. And that <hi>the Law is not made for the righteous.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.) hold, That the Moral Law ought to be caſt quite out of the Church, that we be no more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, or our Conſciences terrified with the preaching thereof, but that we be gently exhorted by the preaching of the Grace of Chriſt: That the Law and Chriſt are two contrary things, whereof one cannot abide the other: That it is of no uſe to a Beleever, no rule for him to walk or examine his life by.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>Chriſt is the end of the Law; <hi>finis perficiens,</hi> not <hi>interficiens. Auguſt.</hi> A conſummating, not conſuming end; not deſtroying, but fulfilling the ſame.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:120048:51"/> So our Saviour himſelf ſays, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17, 19. <hi>I came not to destroy the Law, or the Prophets, but fulfil. Whoſoever therefore ſhall break the least of theſe Commandments, and teach men ſo, &amp;c. Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Do we then make voyd the Law through Faith? God forbid: yea we eſtabliſh the Law.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is nothing, nor uncircumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the keeping the Commandments of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are not under the Law, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Grace;</hi> not under the Law as a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but now as a Father; being freed from the curſe and rigour of it, not obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto it; which we yeeld now, not of compulſion or fear, but love, with all cheerfulneſs and willingneſs, our hearts being enclined and diſpoſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by the work of Gods Spirit. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.3. <hi>This is the love of God that we keep his Commandments, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments are not grievous;</hi> and ſo the Law unto the Regenerate becomes, as it were, Goſpel, even a Law of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The Uſe of the Law is two-fold: 1. Civil to puniſh and reſtrain ſin. 2. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual to reveal it. <hi>Luther in Galat.</hi> In the firſt regard it is not given to the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:120048:52"/> righteous, becauſe good men <hi>are a Law unto themſelves,</hi> Rom. 2.14. The moſt proper and principal Uſe of the Law is to reveal ſin, and ſo the Law is light, not to diſcover grace and life, (this is the office of the Goſpel) but to diſcover ſin and death; therein, as in a glaſs, we may ſee our own blindneſs, &amp;c. For our natures are ſo corrupt, that we ſhould not know they were corrupt but by the Law. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. The Law then ſerves to humble us, and drive us unto Chriſt; to make us know ſin, and ſo know our ſelves, and ſo renounce our ſelves, and fly unto Chriſt. And ſo <hi>the Law is our Schoolmaſter to bring us unto Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3. And <hi>Christ is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs to every one that beleeves, Rom.</hi> 10. becauſe the end of the Law is perfect Righteouſneſs, which we cannot attain of our ſelves, but by Chriſt, who hath fulfilled the ſame for us. And when the Law hath brought us unto Chriſt, it goeth no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the coactive power of it ceaſeth but not the directive: it is ſtill a guide and rule of life unto us, which we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, not to ſeek Righteouſneſs to our ſelves, but to teſtify our thankfulneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:120048:52"/> God; we endeavour to keep the Law, not to juſtify our ſelves, but to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify God, and edify our neighbour by our good example. And therefore we are ſtill exhorted to do the works of the Law, though we ſhall not be juſtified by the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of good works.</head>
               <p>ALthough we are <hi>juſtified freely by the Grace of God through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that is in Jeſus Christ. Rom.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Truth.</note> yet we ought ſtill to maintain good works. 1. Out of thankfulneſs unto God, for ſo great a benefit, and to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify his name. 2. To aſſure our ſelves of the truth of our faith by the fruits thereof. 3. To edify, win and provoke others alſo by our good example.</p>
               <p>Adverſaries are, 1. The <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note> who think good works are meritorious, and ſo overvalue them. 2 The <hi>Libertines</hi> that undervalve them, and think they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant and contrary unto faith; that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:120048:53"/> underſtand our liberty that we have in Chriſt carnally, thinking that now we are freed from all care of good works, and may follow what courſe we pleaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>That we ought to follow good works for the Reaſons before named, is evident by thoſe places of Scripture. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>We are created unto good works that God hath prepared for us, that we ſhould walk in them. Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Who gave himſelf for us, that he might puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie unto himſelf a people zealous of good works.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. We ſhall be judged at the laſt day according to our works; therefore look to your works. So 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.3. And our beſt works have not that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs in them to deſerve at Gods hand; 1. Becauſe they are imperfect. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64.6, They are a debt that we owe unto God: <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10. <hi>When you have done all you can,</hi> or are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do, <hi>ſay you are unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants;</hi> for we do but our duty: we muſt do them, to ſerve, not deſerve. 3. If they were perfect, yet they are Gods, not ours. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>He work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in us both the will and the deed. Joh.</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:120048:53"/> 15. <hi>Without me ye can do nothing.</hi> 4. If we aſcribe merit to our works, we make the death and merits of Chriſt either unneceſſary or inſufficient.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But eternal life is called <hi>a reward. Rom.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. <hi>et</hi> 22.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> There is a reward of debt, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of grace: it is the Apoſtles own diſtinction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4. Heaven and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life is a reward of grace, not of debt. God hath made himſelf a debter to us, not by receiving any thing from us, but by promiſing all things to us. <hi>Auguſt. in Pſalm</hi> 132.2. It is ſaid we ſhall be rewarded not for, but according to our works; the merit of works is plainly ſet aſide: and when God doth crown our works, he doth but crown his own gifts. <hi>Auguſt. Enarr. in Pſalm</hi> 102.3. The Apoſtle calls the reward of ſin wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, becauſe it is of due debt; but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life he calls a gift, becauſe it is not of debt, but grace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. 4. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven is called, not the wages of ſervants, but the inheritance of Saints, or thoſe whom God hath choſen for his children. 5. The good man of the houſe, <hi>(i.)</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. payed at night all his labourers equal wages, to ſhew, that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:120048:54"/> they received a gift of grace, not a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of works.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of Death and Burial.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THere is no man living that ſhal not ſee death; for our life is but a race that will come to an end; and when we have finiſht our courſe here, our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall turn to duſt in the earth, and our ſoul return to God that gave it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>Enemies to this truth were, 1. The old <hi>Hereticks,</hi> called <hi>Nazarens,</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That the ſoul of man, and the ſoul of a beaſt were both of a like nature and ſubſtance: from whence ſprang up thoſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> in <hi>Arabia</hi> the ſtony, called therefore <hi>Arabici,</hi> who affirmed, That the ſoul of man dyes with the body, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the ſoul of a bruit beaſt doth. 2. Others affirmed, That the ſoul did not dye, but ſleep in the grave untill the day of Judgment: Both theſe <hi>Errours</hi> are revived at this day by thoſe that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, The whole man is mortal. And
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:120048:54"/> books are written of the mortality of the ſoul. <hi>Pope John</hi> the 23. was of this opinion, That the ſoul ſhould not ſee God till the day of Judgment. 3. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts</hi> ſay, They ought not to bury the dead, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>let the dead bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the dead.</hi> 4. And thoſe are greatly to be blamed, that deſpiſe Chriſtian bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, and though not guilty of Hereſie, yet of inhumanity, that expoſe their dead friends undecently or irreverently. 5. The <hi>Papists</hi> account burial of the dead a meritorious work; borrowing their authority from the book of <hi>Tobit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſon why the <hi>Arabians</hi> were ſo eaſily taken with this <hi>Errour</hi> of the ſouls mortality, was, becauſe they were,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> and are at this day, a very lewd, diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and theeviſh people; and this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine doth fit ſuch peoples turn very well: and the ſame may be the Reaſon it is received by many at this day; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py were it for them if the ſoul dye, or if it but ſleep till the day of Judgment: it cannot but be a little refreſhing to the thoughts of wicked men, that ſeeing their life ſo uncertain, yet they ſhall not go preſently into torment. But <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.19, 20. is to be underſtood of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:120048:55"/> ſtate of the body after death: for, of the ſoul it is ſaid. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>That the ſoul of man goes upward, and the ſoul of a beaſt goes downward towards the earth. Eccl.</hi> 12.7. <hi>The duſt ſhall return to the earth as it was, and the Spirit ſhall return to God that gave it. Acts</hi> 7.59. <hi>Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus receive my Spirit. Luk.</hi> 23.43. <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> That anſwer of our Saviour to the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducees <hi>Mat</hi> 22.32. puts the Adverſary to ſilence; for <hi>God is not the God of the dead, but of the living.</hi> Laſtly, The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding joys and hopes of good men, and the fears and terrours of wicked men at their departures; are ſufficient Arguments, that the ſoul ſleeps not, but goes preſently to a place of joy or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row whereof the ſoul hath ſome ſecret inklings, inſtinct, or divine aſſurance, and whereunto thoſe hopes and fears ſeem to invite or uſher it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, After the departure of the ſoul, the body ought to be carryed to the grave, and layed up in decent burial, if not out of any regard to the party de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, yet out of reverence to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nature of mankind, or of pure ſhame of that frailty, weakneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:120048:55"/> that our ſelves are ſubject to. The holy <hi>Patriarks,</hi> and all Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of old were very careful of their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers, or burying places, as you may read; and the <hi>Jews</hi> uſed many Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of comlineſs at their burials; not out of any ſuperſtition, but in a godly conſideration of the Reſurrection, in the hope whereof thoſe Ceremonies did ſeem to confirm them; and as that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine grew clearer, ſo theſe Ceremonies grew fewer; as <hi>Tabitha,</hi> her body was only waſhed. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.37. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we condemn thoſe numerous, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, and impious Ceremonies u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the <hi>Papists</hi> at their burials; but yet ſtill we ſhould conſider, that the dead bodies of our godly and Chriſtian friends are precious things, and were the Members of Chriſt, Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhall at the laſt day be raiſed again, and made like unto Chriſts glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body, in hope whereof in mean ſpace we ſhould lay them up, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and reverence: It is no matter to the dead; but 1. It is an honor done to the common nature of mankind. 2. A comfort to ſurviving friends. 3. Many ways uſeful to all that are preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:120048:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of the Reſurrection,</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>ALthough our bodies when we are dead ſhall be turned to duſt and aſhes; yet at the laſt day they ſhall be raiſed again, and be united to our ſouls, and both together be taken into everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting joy, or depart into everlaſting ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>The firſt adverſaries that we read of were the Sadduces, who denyed the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, but were put to ſilence by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. afterwards <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> whoſe words eate like a canker, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17. Then <hi>Simon Magus, Menander,</hi> and their followers. At this day the Familiſts and other fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, will underſtand no reſurrection, but a riſing from ſin: or that the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſpoken of at the laſt day, is not to be underſtood literally of the body naturall, but myſtically of a certain ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall body, that all the Saints ſhall be gathered into, and that the body of fleſh ſhall be annihilated and for ever brought
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:120048:56"/> to nothing. 3. The Manichees imagined a certain Pythagorean tranſmigration of ſouls out of one body into another: and 4. The Anabaptiſts imagine, we ſhall riſe again, but with other new bodies, not the ſame that now we have.</p>
               <p>But 1 Cor. 15.19, 30, 32.<note place="margin">Antidote</note> 
                  <hi>If in this life onely we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men moſt miſerable; why, ſtand we in jeopardie every houre? If the dead riſe not, let us eate and drink, for to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row we ſhal dye:</hi> but be not deceived, for, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28. <hi>The hour ſhal come, that all that be in the grave ſhal hear his voyce,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.52. <hi>For the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſhall ſound and the dead ſhal be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> Revel. 20.13. <hi>The Sea ſhal deliver up the dead that are in it, death and the grave ſhal deliver up the dead that are in them,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>For we muſt al appear before the tribunal of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body.</hi> Job. 19.26. <hi>Though after my skin wormes conſume this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, yet ſhal I ſee God in my fleſh, whom I my ſelf ſhal ſee, and mine eyes ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and none others for me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:120048:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Of Glorification in Heaven.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>ANd whom he Juſtified them he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo glorified; after the reſurrection, and the laſt Judgement is paſt, the Saints or choſen of God, ſhal go with Chriſt in triumph into heaven, and there reign with him for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>
                  <hi>Cerinthus</hi> of old taught, which he ſaid he received by Revelation from Angels, That Chriſt ſhould reign after the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection 1000 yeares, upon earth, where the Saints ſhould enjoy all pleaſures of the fleſh. This doctrine that falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Mahomet</hi> embraced, and put in his Alchoran, and is greedily embraced not onely of his followers, but alſo of the Anabaptiſts and other among us, who expect ſuch a temporary kingdome wherein the godly ſhal reign alone and inherit the earth, after that the wicked be all deſtroyed. The Familiſts ſay, The joyes of heaven are here in this world, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:120048:57"/>
               <p>But 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17.<note place="margin">Antidote</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from heaven</hi> (to what place? to the earth? no; but) <hi>then we that are alive ſhal be caught up together with them, in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the ayre, and ſo ſhal we ever be with the Lord.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. <hi>When this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle is diſſolved (i.)</hi> when we dye, our next building or habitation to dwell in, is <hi>eternal in the heavens.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The inheritance of the Saints is reſerved in heaven for them.</hi> where, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. a Crown is laid up for them, and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. things prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for them that the heart of man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive. But <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>their vile body ſhal be made like the glorious body of Chriſt. Dan.</hi> 12.3. They ſhall ſhine as ſtars for ever and ever, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.5. the Saints ſhal raign in heaven for ever and ever; as for thoſe 2000 years <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. they are to be underſtood of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Saints in this preſent world, when Satan was bound 1000 years that he could not deceive the Nations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:120048:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Of Hell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>BUt the Reprobates, wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y men after they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their fearfull doome, ſhal go into the everlaſting torment of hell fire, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the devil and his Angels.</p>
               <p>There be ſome that ſay there is neither Devill nor hell:<note place="margin">Errours.</note> no Devil or evill ſpirit but a mans own vile affections: nor hel, but a mans own evill conſcience. 2. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay there is a hell, but not till the day of Judgement. 3. Others, that hell tormen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are not everlaſting, but that the damned and devils themſelves ſhall be ſaved at laſt: as a Sect of old cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therefore <hi>Liberatores</hi> ſayd; or as many as in hell call for mercy, ſay the Turks.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>But, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>The Angels which fel at the beginning were caſt down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hel, and delivered into chains of darkneſſe,</hi> Jude 6. <hi>Everlaſting chains,</hi> where, 2 Theſſ. 1.9. <hi>Their deſtruction ſhal be everlaſting,</hi> Mar. 9.44. <hi>Their
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:120048:58"/> worm never dyes, their fire never is quenched,</hi> Revel. 20.10. <hi>Are tormented day and night for ever and ever:</hi> there were devils then and a hel from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; into which, with the Devill and his Angels, the reprobates, all wicked men are caſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. not for a time but for ever: for out of hell there is no Redemption, <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.26. betwixt that and heaven there is a great gulf fixt, ſo that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re is no paſſing between, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29. <hi>Oh that men were wiſe! then they would underſtand this, they would conſider their latter end.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>Of Purgatory.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is no other third or middle place between Heaven and Hell,<note place="margin">Truth.</note> whereunto the ſouls departed do go: And therefore the doctrine of Purgatory with all its appendices, as pardons, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the dead, &amp;c. are not only fond vain and unwarrantable, but heatheniſh alſo, &amp; blaſphemous.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:120048:59"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>This was a device of the old Heathens; was received among Chriſtians, firſt by <hi>Simon Magus, Montanus,</hi> and other leud <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and is now embraced by none but the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> through the covetouſneſs and filthy lucre of their Clergy, becauſe it fils not only the Popes coffers, but alſo the private purſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very maſs Prieſt. The place they ſay is next unto hell: the pains of it are all one with hell fire, though ſome mitigate the matter: But King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> reſolved this doubt beſt of any. The time it laſts, is till the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at utmoſt, no longer; and yet if ſurviving friends wil pay, the Prieſt pray, or the Pope but ſay the word, they may be releaſed at any time ſooner. It was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented for the purging of ſouls departed, which had not fully fatisfied in this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>But as there be but two ſorts of men in this world, ſo there are but two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces prepared for them in the world to come; and as there are but two places, ſo there are but two ways and gates that lead unto thoſe two places. Whereof you read, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13, 14. If there were a third place, certainly our Saviour, who came to teach, and afterwards ſent his
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:120048:59"/> Spirit to lead us in the way of all truth, would have ſhewed us the way to that place too. But ſeeing the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves could never yet agree about the place where, the pains what, or the time how long it ſhall laſt; and that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Doctour of the <hi>Porphyry</hi> Chair cannot reſolve it, nor will of his charity releaſe them without money, as they ſay he can for money; we leave it as a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh and ſottiſh invention: and if there be no purgatory, then pardons, and prayers for the dead are of no uſe; and howſoever the pardons of a ſinful man, or the man of ſin cannot be of any value. An Iriſh Gentleman, and a Papiſt, being upon a former agreement to pay a certain ſum of money to a Prieſt for Maſſes ſaid, for delivering his fathers ſoul out of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; brought the money and laid it down: But quoth he to the Prieſt, be ye ſure now that my fathers ſoul is clear out? Yes, I'le warrant you quoth the Prieſt: Nay then quoth the Gentleman, by my troth I have even done a childs part; if he be out, let him take heed how he comes there again; and ſo putting up his money gave the Prieſt the baffle, Countermining one cheat with another.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:120048:60"/> If all Papiſts would ſerve their Prieſts ſo, and Pope too, it would prove the beſt Antidote againſt this Hereſie: For mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is the fuel that feeds this fire, (if it be fire, and not water, as ſome learned Papiſts have doubted it is.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Of Images.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THe worſhip of Images, Reliques, the Croſs, &amp;c. are not only vain, unwarrantable, and contrary to Gods Word, but alſo heatheniſh and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatry.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>The Papiſts, not only erect and adore Images themſelves, but alſo accurſe and condemn as Hereticks to the fire, yea to hell fire all thoſe that will not do the like. 2. The <hi>Pſeudo-Lutherans</hi> retain Images in their Churches, eſteeming them not onely as Ornaments, but alſo as lay-mens books, to edifie, admoniſh, and put them in mind of ſome heavenly things, but yet allow them not to be worſhipped; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing herein like the <hi>Turks,</hi> who in the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:120048:60"/> ſack of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſeeing the Temple of Saint <hi>Sophia,</hi> a goodly ſtructure, and the marble pillars enameled and filleted with the pictures of Saints, were loth to deface ſuch goodly pieces, though I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages are contrary to their Law, and Religion, but only put out their eyes. Images were creeping in apace here in <hi>England;</hi> and I ſaw once the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lady wrought upon the Communion Table, or Altar cloth, as it was called, in a Church held in <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> by Biſhop <hi>Goodman</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> which I note above all other, becauſe it is a fabulous legend that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves ſcarce admit.</p>
               <p>The old heathen <hi>Romans</hi> for a long time had no Images,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> accounting it ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg to preſent heavenly things by earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forms; ſeeing we cannot poſſibly any way attain unto the knowledg of God, but in mind and underſtanding. <hi>Plut. in Vita Numae.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> have none; nor the <hi>Jews,</hi> as contrary to Gods Law. The ancient Chriſtians would not ſuffer an Image ſo much as in the Church-porch, ſo jealous they were of Idolatry ſtealing in. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> think they quit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of Idolatry, when they ſay they
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:120048:61"/> worſhip not the Image, but the Saint or diety in the Image: But the ſame excuſe is made by <hi>Plutarch</hi> for the heathen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, who were none of them ſo ſottiſh to take the Images of wood and ſtone for Gods able to help them. God forbad not only graven Images to be worſhipt, but alſo himſelf to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt in the Image. <hi>If we make an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the true God to worſhip, then we fall either</hi> 1. <hi>into Idolatry by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Image, or</hi> 2. <hi>Errour and Hereſie by aſcribing to God a bodily ſhape, which he hath not.</hi> Abulenſis <hi>in Deut. cap.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>The Images of Saints are not to be worſhipt, becauſe the Saints themſelves are not to be worſhipt. The worſhip of Angels is expreſly forbidden, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18. and the Angels themſelves forbid it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. &amp; 22.9. with this Reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are our brethren, and fellow ſervants: Much leſs the Sains, whoſe greateſt honor is to be but as the Angels. <hi>Mat.</hi> And the livelieſt picture of Chriſt is in the Scriptures, there he is painted before our eyes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. A man may look upon a Crucifix as long as he lives, and never the wiſer, never the holier.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:120048:61"/> In the Bible you have a ſpeaking picture of Chriſt; in a diſtreſſed brother, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Crucifix; in the holy Supper, a more lively Image of his death &amp; paſſion, then any painter can deviſe, and ſhew us thoſe holy Myſteries that a picture can never do.</p>
               <p>Images, though not worſhipped, yet are not uſeful but hurtful, in the place of Gods Worſhip; the picture of Chriſt is ſo far from putting us in mind of him, that it draws our minds from him, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our imagination to a corporal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. <hi>Few pray before an Image, but they pray likewiſe unto it, a ſecret be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief ſtealing into their minds, that when they look upon it they think it hears them. Auguſt. Enarrat. in Pſalm</hi> 113. And therefore another ſays, it is <hi>Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae deceptionis inventum,</hi> one of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels Arch-cheats.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:120048:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THe Church is the body of Chriſt, or the Church is the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Gods Elect called and gathered by his holy Word and Spirit out of all mankinde from the beginning to the end of the world, into one fellowſhip with Chriſt, and communion one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And although many are called and but few choſen, many are joyned unto the Church that are not united unto Chriſt, hold outward communion with the Saints that have no inward fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Son of God, yet we are in charity to account all thoſe for mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the true Church, that are out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly called, and accordingly make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the true Faith, until the Lord the ſearcher of all hearts, who alone knoweth who are his, do make the truth appear, as he ſhall do at the great day of his appearing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note>Adverſaries to this truth are; 1. Thoſe that ſay, there is no true Church upon
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:120048:62"/> earth, as the Seekers do. 2. Thoſe that would have the viſible Church to be voyd of ſin and ſinners, as the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Familiſts, Browniſts, and all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts. 3. That will have the true Catholick Church to be a mixt company of good and bad together, as the Papiſts do. 4. The ſame Papiſts to the great contumely and reproach of Chriſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their Pope to be head of the Church. 5. To uphold their Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Synagogue, among many other they maintain three ſpecial errours that are the very props and pillars of the ſame: <hi>ſc.</hi> That the Church cannot err: That the Church is alwayes viſible: That the Word and Sacraments are not proper marks of the true Church. 6. The Anabaptiſts abuſe the communion of Saints in the Church, to bring in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of goods in the civil ſtate, and make all things common.</p>
               <p>The word, Church,<note place="margin">Antidote</note> Chyrch or Kirch we borrow of the Duch, among whom it is commonly taken for <hi>Gotteſhauſe,</hi> Gods houſe or the place of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. It ſeems to come of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or by contraction of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lords or the Lords houſe; the material temple is
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:120048:63"/> Gods houſe: <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.21. and ſo are the Saints too: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.22. But the word that properly ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the congregation or aſſembly of the Saints, and is ſo often in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment tranſlated [Church] is <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> and this alſo is applied by S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the place of divine worſhip or meeting place: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 22. The name of Church then is not ſo peculiar to the Saints, but that it belongs alſo to the place of their publick meeting, and therefore they are much to blame, that make ſuch a needleſs ado about the word, in deriſion calling our Churches Steeplehouſes &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But taking the word only for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly or company of the faithful, we affirm,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, That there is, and ever hath been a Church upon earth; the Church conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Abel, Seth, Enoch, Noah,</hi> and their families, till <hi>Abraham;</hi> In his poſterity to Chriſt; and then the walls of the Church were enlarged by pulling down the partition wall, and calling in the Gentiles: <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. Churches were gathered and confirmed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles;
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:120048:63"/> men ſet apart for the work of the Miniſtry; <hi>Acts</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. and thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſo had authority given them to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate and ordain others alſo to the ſame work: <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. and ſo to continue ſucceſſively in all ages, as it hath done to this day. And now where the ſame Goſpel is truly preached, the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments duly adminiſtred, Beleevers profeſſing the ſame Faith, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the ſame ordinances, as at this day are in <hi>England, Scotland &amp;c.</hi> there is a true Church of Chriſt as was in the Apoſtles times.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, The true Catholick Church is the company of Gods Elect only; whereof it is ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for it,</hi> Eph. 5.25. This is the <hi>Church of the firſt born, who are written in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> Heb. 12.22. <hi>The body of Chriſt,</hi> Col. 1.18. <hi>The houſhold of God,</hi> Eph. 2.23, In which is no condemnation, and out of which is no ſalvation: and of this Church, hypocrites or wicked men are not members; for <hi>what fellowſhip hath Chriſt with Belial?</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16. This Church is both inviſible and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible; the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:120048:64"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, many are in the Church that are not of it: outwardly called not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly: from whence ariſeth that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of the viſible and inviſible Church: The inviſible are the Elect only, ſo called, becauſe their faith whereby, and the body whereinto they are incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate are both inviſible. The viſible Church is the whole company of thoſe that joyn in one outward league and profeſſion: The ground of this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is laid by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20 16 and hereunto belongs that parable of the tares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. whereby we are warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that although tares may grow, <hi>(i.)</hi> wicked men or hypocrites may live in a viſible Church, yet not to condemn it, or ſeparate our ſelves as the manner of ſome is, leſt we forſake and condemn a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Gods choſen, but to eſteem it for all that as a true Church, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or more principal part, <hi>(i.)</hi> the Elect that are in it; even as S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> a Church of God, though there were Hereticks, Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and inceſtuous perſons among them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Fourthly, As the Church is the body of Chriſt, ſo Chriſt is the head of the Church, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23. And there
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:120048:64"/> can be none other, becauſe none elſe can give life, ſenſe and motion to that body: and ſo the Pope cannot be head of the Church: Not a temporal or ſecular head, becauſe the kingdom of Chriſt, that is, his Church, is not of this world: Not a ſpiritual head, becauſe he cannot give ſpiritual life and grace: Nor a miniſterial head, becauſe he cannot mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Word and Sacraments to all Churches in the world, neither doth it to his own paſtoral charge; and there can be no other reaſon why he ſhould be called a miniſterial head, but for this miniſtry. He cannot be the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eutenant General or Vicar of Chriſt: for a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant ſuppoſeth the abſence of him whoſe place he holdeth: but Chriſt is always preſent with his Church himſelf; and ſo there is no room for the Popes Vicarage.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Fifthly, The Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Judea,</hi> who are now faln and become no Churches, are ſufficient witneſſes to this truth, that no Church on earth is priviledged or freed from errour. Not the Church of Rome; ſpecially being guided by ſuch a head as the Pope is, who being but a man, may err; that man
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:120048:65"/> of ſin, and cannot but err: moſt of their Popes for many hundred of years have erred, both in matter of Faith and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; their own Hiſtories teſtifie that they have been Negromancers, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juers, Blaſphemers, Hereticks, Athieſts, Adulterers, Murderers, inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c. They have done and do ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deny Chriſt, perſecute his Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn his truth, deride his Goſpel, tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his holy ordinances into ridiculou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mock-ſhews: and therefore the Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Rome can no longer juggle and hide her abominable errours under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended infallibility of ſuch a miſcrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 2. Although Chriſt hath and ever had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church viſible upon earth, ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Beleevers making profeſſion of the ſame common Faith, yet it hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and may come to paſs, that either through the infirmity of ſome that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcern it, the malice of others that will not acknowledge it, or throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſecution being driven into corners, the Church may lie hidden as it did i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the days of <hi>Elias,</hi> 1 King. 19.10. th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it may not be viſible to every eye: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Papiſts ask then, where was the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Church before <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:120048:65"/> the Roman Church were not it? We anſwer, it was in the wilderneſs; and yet in thoſe darkeſt times of Popery, it was not ſo over-ſhadowed, but that the very flames of perſecution did diſcover what and where it was, plainly diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true ſheep of Chriſt from thoſe helliſh wolves. 3. The marks or notes of the true Church, are the ſame whereby it was at firſt called and gathered, <hi>ſc.</hi> the preaching of the Word and adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sacraments: thoſe 15. ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in their place by the Romaniſts, are uncertain, and may moſt of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with a Synagogue of Satan, as well as a Church of Chriſt, as Antiquity, Multitude, Miracles, &amp;c. For that old Serpent had a Synagogue from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: and the primitive Church was a true Church though not ancient: Chriſts Church is a little flock; and Antichriſt come ſhal with lying wonders &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> Sixthly, The Church is a ſpiritual Commonwealth, and the communion of Saints is ſpiritual, not temporal, in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling the mounds of private poſſeſſions and laying all things common.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.32. <hi>they had all things in common.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:120048:66"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> It is anſwered <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. <hi>whiles it remained was it not thine own? and after it was ſold, was it not in thine own power?</hi> The community ſpoken of was only of things dedicated to the Churches treaſury for relief of poor brethren, there remaining ſtill ſomething to a man that was proper to himſelf, and a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to retain what part he pleaſed, as is plain. For otherwiſe, if all things were common, to what purpoſe are we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to liberality? What need <hi>Paul</hi> work with his own hands? or how could he be burthenſom to any one, if all things were common?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Though the Church be but one, as there is but one Faith &amp;c. yet it is diſtinguiſhed into Catholick or Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal and Particular: The Catholick ſo called, becauſe it comprehends the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of all times and places: the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar named according to the place where that part is ſeated. The Roman Church then is unduly called Catholick, becauſe it is a particular Heretical Church, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther univerſal nor orthodox: Thoſe are miſtaken and to blame that call the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Catholicks, becauſe they profeſs not the Catholick faith, or faith of the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:120048:66"/> Catholick Church: neither is their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion the old Religion, but new and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart, being a fardel of late humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, not at all to be found in any ſacred Record.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> Of the Sacraments.</head>
               <p>THe Sacraments are holy and viſible ſignes and ſeals ordained of God,<note place="margin">Truth.</note> the more fully to declare and aſſure unto us the promiſe of the Goſpel. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the New Teſtament are only two, Baptiſm and the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>Adverſaries are, 1.<note place="margin">Errours.</note> Thoſe Hereticks both old and new that deny all Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſaying they are of no uſe in the Church. 2. The Anabaptiſts think, there is no other uſe or end of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but only to ſerve as badges of our Chriſtian Profeſſion. 3. The Papiſts ſay the Sacraments confer grace by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the work done. And 4. That there are ſeven Sacraments of the New Teſtament; and hold them accurſed that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:120048:67"/> ſay there are fewer, or that they are not all truly and properly Sacraments ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>Although the name of Sacrament be not to be found in the Scriptures, yet we find Myſtery there, a word of the ſame ſignification; and the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were ordained by Chriſt in the Scriptures: <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go teach all nations baptizing them &amp;c.</hi> Luk. 22.19, 20. <hi>He took bread &amp;c. and after ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per took the cup &amp;c. ſaying, Do this in remembrance of me.</hi> And God hath ordained the Sacraments, not to be bare ſignes, but ſeals alſo and pledges to aſſure us of the promiſes made in his Word; and ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. calls cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, <hi>a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of faith:</hi> Not as if the Sacrament gives ſtrength to the promiſe as weak of it ſelf, but as a ſeal confirms and aſſures it to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, Although the Sacraments do not confer grace, yet they are a means to convey it unto us; for being ſenſible elements that may be ſeen, felt and taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, every ſence is a pipe or conduit, as it were, to draw and convey from the outward element, the thing thereby ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:120048:67"/> to the inward underſtanding. Yet this is done, not by vertue of the work done, or by uttering certain words, but by the vertue of Gods ordinance and power of the holy Ghoſt working with the ſame. If the Sacraments did contain grace eſſentially within them, as Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine in a box, then indeed it might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that by the outward work done grace ſhould be conferred; but we ſee the contrary; <hi>That inviſible ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath been without the viſible ſigns: and again the viſible ſignes have been given without true ſanctification,</hi> Aug. <hi>in Levit. qu.</hi> 84. as we ſee in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Centurion and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus.</hi> And therefore alſo though the Sacraments cannot be deſpiſed or neglected (being Gods ordinances) without great impiety and unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards him, who by them hath ſo tenderly provided for our weakneſs, yet they are not ſo abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, that without them it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be ſaved; for God is above his ordinances, and can ſave us without them. <hi>It is not the want but contempt of the Sacraments that is dangerous and damnable:</hi> Bernard.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:120048:68"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Laſtly, There are but two Sacraments only of the New Teſtament; Baptiſm and the Lords Supper; we read of no more ordained by Chriſt, who only hath power to ordain Sacraments; and this was done in regard of our weakneſs that we ſhould not be over-burthened. <hi>Some few ſignes for many were delivered unto us, and the ſame in doing most eaſie; in underſtanding moſt holy; in obſerving most pure, as are Baptiſm and the Lords Supper:</hi> Auguſt. <hi>lib. de Doct. Chriſt. c.</hi> 9. And therefore thoſe five other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments reckoned by the Church of Rome are not Sacraments of the New Teſtament, neither have any Warrant in Gods Word. For, 1. Penance and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony cannot be Sacraments of the New Teſtament, becauſe they were in being and as neceſſary both before and under the Law as now they are. 2. The uſe of Matrimony belongs to Heathens as well as Chriſtians. 3. The Papiſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict themſelves, for they accurſe thoſe that ſhall ſay the Sacraments are not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation: <hi>Concil. Trident. Seſſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Can.</hi> 4. and yet debar their Prieſts from Matrimony, which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count one of thoſe Sacraments; and ſo
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:120048:68"/> highly extol ſingle life in all, as if there were no other way to heaven for any. They ſay the Sacraments confer grace, and yet deny Matrimony to their Prieſts, and ſo deprive them of that grace that Matrimony might confer upon them, and ſo keep them honeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>Of Baptiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BAptiſm is the Sacrament of admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or entrance into the Church,<note place="margin">Truth.</note> wherein by the outward waſhing or ſprinkling of the body with water, the inward cleanſing of the ſoul from ſin, thorough the ſprinkling of the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, and waſhing of the Holy Ghoſt is ſigned and ſealed unto us. The Baptiſm of Infants is in any wiſe to be retained in the Church as moſt agreeable with the inſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Adverſaries; 1.<note place="margin">Errours.</note> Some explode Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm quite out of the Church, as ſome Hereticks of old, and now adays do. 2. Others allow it to folk of riper years,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:120048:69"/> but deny it to children, as the Pelagians did and Anabaptiſts do, and both upon the ſame ground; ſome of them ſay it is an horrible abomination. 3. Some eſteem of Baptiſm as a thing indifferent. 4. The Papiſts ſay it is abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, that children dying without it are not ſaved. 5. Laſtly, the ſame Papiſts alſo abuſe and adulterate this holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, adding to the element of water, ſalt, ſpittle, oyl, &amp;c. uſing tapers, exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms and other ſilly ceremonies, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as they reckon 22. and alſo prophane the ſame in applying it to things without reaſon and life, as bells, banners, ſwords and daggers, and that to bloody ends, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>That Baptiſm was ordained &amp; comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our bleſſed Savior is expreſly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 29.19. whereunto is annexed a promiſe of ſalvation, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. And therefore it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not a thing indifferent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is an ordinance of Chriſt, nor yet abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, as hath been ſaid before. Baptiſm is called <hi>the lavacre of regeneration,</hi> Tit. 3.5. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. it is ſaid, <hi>Except a man be born again of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:120048:69"/> not that any part of our Regeneration is aſcribed to water, but only by water the office of the Holy Ghoſt is declared; as alſo by fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. which ſome miſtaking, did brand their children with a hot iron. Though the outward waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of water then be not the very waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away of ſin, yet it is ſo called, the ſign borrowing the name of the thing ſignified, for the more forcible perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our hearts, and ſtronger confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Faith, that our eyes are not fed with bare ſigns, but preſented with the thing it ſelf, and that our ſins are as certainly done away by the blood of Chriſt, as our bodies are cleanſed by the waſhing of water.</p>
               <p>To let paſs thoſe ridiculous toies of ſalt, ſpittle and other ſtuff uſed by the <hi>Papists:</hi> the main difference at this day among us is concerning circumſtance of time. The <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> deny Infant-baptiſm, and both up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ground. With this <hi>Errour</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> many godly people are entangled, that are free enough from the reſt of that peſtilent Sect. Their Reaſons are, 1. Becauſe there is neither precept nor example for it. 2. Infants do
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:120048:70"/> not beleeve, but it is ſayed. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. <hi>If thou beleeveſt, thou mayſt be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> It is anſwered: To the firſt, That there is both precept and example for Infant-baptiſm: the precept is <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. the examples are <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15, 33. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16. where Infants are included as part of the nations and houſholds: and although there be no expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for baptizing Infants, yet ſeeing alſo there is no expreſs exception, they muſt be baptized, or elſe thoſe general precepts and examples, including all, both Infants as well as men, are not follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and obſerved. And if it be ſufficient Reaſon againſt Infant-baptiſm, that there is no expreſs precept or example for it, then let the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for ſhame leave off that ſhameful ſtripping and dipping their proſelytes, or elſe ſhew me where they have any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command or example for it. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, They that do not beleeve muſt not be baptized: but Infants do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; <hi>Ergo.</hi> Whoſoever doth not labor ſhall not eat. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. But Infants cannot labour; <hi>Ergo.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Both theſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſomewhat alike, and neither good, becauſe that is drawn to Infants,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:120048:70"/> which belongs only to men of years. And indeed this latter is the better of the two, becauſe it hath an expreſs text for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, which the other hath not. But to remove that rub of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> out of the way, concerning the Faith of Infants: We ſay, 1. That they have reaſonable ſouls, faculties of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and will, which are the ſeat of Faith, and the weakneſs of the Organs cannot hinder the power of the Holy Ghoſt to work Faith in them, if he pleaſe. 2. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith there is no ſalvation; if Infants then have not Faith, the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> muſt ſhew ſome other way of ſalvation beſides Faith in Chriſt, or elſe conclude, that all Infants dying are damned; but yet I hope they will not paſs this cruel ſentence upon them, unleſs they provide a Limbus, or place of eaſe for them, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do. 3. Circumciſion is <hi>the ſeal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, Rom.</hi> 4.11. And yet it was adminiſtred to Infants: Infants therefore ought to be baptized; and as good reaſon there is to baptiſe as there was to circumciſe them. 4. We have many preſidents of children that were regenerate and ſanctified; as of <hi>Jeremiah, John Baptiſt, &amp;c.</hi> who were
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:120048:71"/> filled with the Holy Ghoſt from the womb: and if children have the Holy Ghoſt, then they may be baptized. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.47. <hi>Can any man forbid water, that theſe ſhould be baptized who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Holy Ghoſt as well as we?</hi> 5. Our Saviour himſelf teſtifieth in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words, That Infants beleeve in him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.6, And that babes and ſucklings confeſs him, and bear witneſs unto his name. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.16. And did grace them with many favours, own them for the children of God, taking them in his arms, laying his hands upon them, and bleſſing them, ſaying, That to them belongs the Kingdom of God: Who then ſhall be ſo bold or impious to refuſe and reject thoſe that our Saviour himſelf received and embraced ſo loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, giving ſuch gracious teſtimoneis of them? with whom God entered into Covenant, as well as with their parents. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. And unto whom the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God were made, as well as unto them? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39.</p>
               <p>But (ſay the <hi>Anabaptists</hi>) how ſhal we know that children believe? And (ſaith one) If I had a certificate from God, that a child believes, I would not
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:120048:71"/> ſtick at his Baptiſme: Let them tell us, what infallible certificate they have for men of riper years? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do not plunge more hypocrites and unbelievers in their flouds, then we ſprinkle at our fonts, is a queſtion to be made. But the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> contradict themſelves, croſſing one Argument with another, overthrowing their own grounds, and deſtroying the foundation that themſelves have layd. As for their ſtripping, it is againſt common honeſty and modeſty; and that dipping is not neceſſary to be uſed, is clear by their own Argument, becauſe they have no where one expreſs word of command or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it: And alſo, the blood of Chriſt is called the blood of ſprinkling, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. And as it was typified under the Law by divers ſprinklings, ſo it is expreſt under the Goſpel by ſprinkling as well as dipping.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:120048:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Of the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THE Lords Supper is the Sacrament of Preſervation in the Church; wherein by the ſigns of bread and wine, are ſignified, ſealed, and exhibited to every faithful receiver, the body and blood of Chriſt, for his ſpiritual nouriſhment and continual growth in him unto life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adverſaries</hi> of old were many, that did either deſpiſe and refuſe this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, or abuſe or prophane it, either mingling, adding, or altering and change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Elements, and ſubſtituting others in their places. But to let them paſs, at this day the principal <hi>Errours</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Errours.</note> are theſe three.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>The firſt is of Tranſubſtantiation, and that holdeth, that after the words of Conſecration, and by vertue of the ſame, there is a converſion or turning of the bread and wine into the body and blood of Chriſt, ſo that the very true and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral body of Chriſt is corporally preſent
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:120048:72"/> and carnally eaten in the Sacrament, the ſubſtance of bread and wine being va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht away, nothing remaining thereof, but only the outward accidents to ſerve the ſenſes. The firſt occaſion of this he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie ſeems to be given by the <hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naites,</hi> John 6.52. but was confirmed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this title by the Councel of <hi>Lateran,</hi> called againſt <hi>Berengarius</hi> in the yeare 1215; and this is now the opinion of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> followed with many Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Idolatries, and ridiculous Mumme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is of Conſubſtantiation, invented by ſome, who, to ſhun the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities of the former opinion fell into worſe, affirming, That the ſubſtance of bread and wine, and of the body and blood of Chriſt, are joyntly, or both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, bodily preſent, and eaten in the Sacrament; the body of Chriſt being in, with, and under the bread. The firſt Author of this opinion, and the time when it began is uncertainly reported; and although it were long before <hi>Luther,</hi> yet it was taken up in haſte by him about the year 1525. is ſtill maintained by his followers, and gave occaſion to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue that bowing and cringing that was
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:120048:73"/> lately uſed to the Communion Table.</p>
               <p>The third is of bare figure, and only ſignification, affirming, That in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament there is nothing but bread and wine, bare ſigns, and no other preſence of Chriſts body but only in figure and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification; ſo that the faithful receive nothing but naked and bare ſigns. The foundation of this <hi>Errour</hi> was layd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout four hundred years after Chriſt, by ſome <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that came as ſhort of this myſtery, as the <hi>Capernaites</hi> went too far, making no account of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſaying, that it did neither good nor hurt. This <hi>Errour</hi> was ſet on foot again by <hi>Caroloſtadius,</hi> a raſh-brained man, about the year 1524. and is now followed by the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>The doctrin of our Church <hi>Art.</hi> 28. is the ſame that the Apoſtle delivers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. To all the three Adverſaries together we ſay; If there be nothing in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament but bare ſigns, why doth our Saviour ſay of the elements, <hi>This is my body, and this is my blood?</hi> And S. <hi>Paul, The bread which we break is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body of Chriſt.</hi> If his body and blood be not there at all? And if his body and blood be there corporally
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:120048:73"/> and carnally, preſent, even whole Chriſt, why then doth our Saviour ſay, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me?</hi> And St. <hi>Paul, Ye ſhew forth the Lords death till he come?</hi> 1 Cor. 10. And St. <hi>Peter,</hi> That <hi>the heavens ſhall receive him</hi> to the end of the world. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. Refuſing then and denying, both Tranſubſtantiation, and Conſubſtantiation, as more then our Saviour intended in theſe words <hi>(This is my body, &amp;c.)</hi> And alſo bare ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation as a great deal leſs; we admit and acknowledg Tranſmutation, or a change, and that great and marvellous, in the uſe of the Elements; not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but in vertue, power and operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ſanctified ſigns are, in ſubſtance, creatures; in ſignification, myſteries; in operation, the things themſelves, whoſe names they bear; the change is in their operation and uſe, and therefore alſo in their names: <hi>For Chriſt hath honoured the Symboles with the names, or appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his body and blood, not change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their nature, but adding grace unto nature.</hi> Theodoret in Dial.</p>
               <p>In the Sacrament then, there muſt needs be more then bare ſigns, or naked Elements, for how ſhould earthly bread
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:120048:74"/> be an Inſtrument of heavenly grace and life to quicken and ſtrengthen the ſoul, but by ſome great and marvellous change? which change is not in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the creatures, but in their vertue, power and operation; and ſuch vertue, power and operation could not be, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the very body and blood of Chriſt were truly preſent, truly given, and truly received in the Sacrament: And yet the body and blood of Chriſt is not preſent, given or received corporally and carnally; the bread and wine being turned into the body and blood of Chriſt, as the Papiſts affirm: For, 1. It is contrary to the Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. Where after conſecration they are called bread and wine. 2. It overthrows the nature of a Sacrament, for where is no Element, there can be no Sacrament. 3. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to nature it ſelf, that an accident ſhould be without its ſubject. 4. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience dayly ſhews, that the Elements by continuance corrupt, by eating nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the body, go down into the belly, &amp;c. which cannot be ſaid of accidents, or of the body and blood of Chriſt. 5. A carnal eating is unavailable to ſalvation, (by the Papiſts own confeſſion) unleſs
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:120048:74"/> it be done by Faith; but receiving by Faith without carnal eating is available. <hi>Concil. Trident. Seſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>et Cat. Rom.</hi> Why then is it contended for? Laſtly, It is contrary to their own Canon taken out of St. <hi>Auguſtine. Can. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Quid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But Chriſt himſelf ſaid, <hi>This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> the night before he dyed, no time to utter dark Parables, but plain words.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                  </label> He took the cup alſo and ſaid, <hi>This is my blood,</hi> Mark 14.23.24. If you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it litterally, then the cup and not the wine muſt be turned into blood: but if here be a plain figure, (their ſubtileſt Doctours cannot tell how to avoyd it) then why not a time to ſpeak in figures? Why not <hi>(This is my body)</hi> a figure too?</p>
               <p>But when our Saviour ſays, <hi>This is my body,</hi> he doth not intend to ſhew what the bread is, but what his body is; not that the bread is turned into his fleſh, but that his body is food for our ſouls, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as bread is for our bodies: It ſhews not any converſion of one ſubſtance into another, but only the relation that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. <hi>He which before called his body bread,</hi> John 6. <hi>doth now call the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:120048:75"/> bread his body, that by this cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge of names we might understand and beleeve the change that is made by grace; and not ſo much heed the things we ſee, as mind the the things we ſee not.</hi> Theod. Dialog. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why doſt thou prepare thy teeth and thy belly? This is no meat for the belly, but for the mind; beleeve and thou haſt eaten.</hi> Auguſtine in Joan. Tract. 25. ad cap. 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſubſtantiation is farther from the truth then Tranſubſtantiation; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo poſſible nor probable: It is not ſo likely or agreeable to our Saviours words, who ſays, <hi>This is my body,</hi> and not, my body is in, with, or under the bread. And yet they are both groſs <hi>Errours,</hi> and the occaſions of groſs Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. They are both far from our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviours meaning, when he ſpake the words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſenſe. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. From the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Ancient Fathers, who call the elements, ſigns, figures, types, &amp;c. of the body and blood of Chriſt: and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſays, the words <hi>(this is my body)</hi> are to be underſtood in a figurative, not a litteral ſenſe. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>de
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:120048:75"/> Doct. Chriſt.</hi> And beſides they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible in nature.</p>
               <p>But ſetting aſide that barren opinion of bare ſign and figure, the queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the reſt is not about the ſubſtance of the thing; for we confeſs, That the very body and blood of Chriſt is given and received; all the queſtion is about the manner: they ſay it is corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and carnally; we grant indeed it is really, if by really you underſtand truly, and indeed, but yet that it is ſpiritual, heavenly, and divine: The matter of the thing preſent the Apoſtle ſhews plainly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. But for the manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, we have no ſuch evident demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. To conclude, the truth is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the ſigns, the Holy Spirit with the Sacrament, feeding our ſouls with the truth of Chriſts body and blood; but the inviſible working of that Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit herein is unſearchable, the natural man cannot perceive it, becauſe it is ſpiritual: Let us firmly beleeve then what we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive, and reſt aſſured in this truth, that we receive in the Sacrament the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body and blood of Chriſt by Faith, though we cannot conceive it by ſenſe or reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:120048:76"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>Of Reformation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Truth.</note>THere is no particular Church on earth, and never was ſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged, but that it may and many have faln into dangerous Errours both of life and doctrine, as the examples of all both former and latter times have witneſſed; ſo that there is no Church conſiſting of men that may err, but may need Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, even as a material building doth need often reparation. And for as much as many horrible abuſes and ſuperſtitions were lately brought, through the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of ſome, into the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, to the great diſhonor of Almighty God, the decay of piety, and imminent ruine of the true Proteſtant Religion, therefore this preſent Reformation was extreamly neceſſary; and is no Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a Reſtauration only of our Church to its ancient purity of doctrine, diſcipline and divine worſhip, as it was eſtabliſhed by the noble Princes <hi>K. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> 6. and <hi>Q. Elizabeth</hi> of famous memories.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:120048:76"/>
               <p>Although this truth be as clear as the light,<note place="margin">Errours.</note> as ſhall immediately be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and that this preſent Reformation hath caſt out many groſs abuſes, that contrary to the determinations of our Church have been lately put upon us, yet there are divers adverſaries that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of malice, or ignorance, or both, do ſtill with all their might oppoſe it: And ſo I ſhall reduce them all under three heads: The firſt is of thoſe that do it of pure malice, as all lewd and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perſons, who hate all reformation whatſoever, that ſhal hedg up their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant ways, and give a check or ſtop to their looſe courſes; among theſe we may reckon ſome Papiſts and other Sectaries. The ſecond is of thoſe that do it of meer ignorance, as divers civil Proteſtants, that think no Religion ſo ancient as that they were bred in; and ſtrangely miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Church-men for the Church, take up moſt of their religion upon their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. The third ſort do it of malice and ignorance both; as divers fiery ſpirits, that think there is no way to reform the Church, unleſs they pull it to pieces, as if there were no way to cure the head-ache but to knock a mans brains out. There
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:120048:77"/> be alſo divers hypocrites that can drive on a reformation for their own ends and advantages, and yet are as great enemies to the truth of it as any of the former.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antidote</note>I ſhall endeavor to ſatisfie the honeſt Proteſtant, that is engaged againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation for want of better informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and would ſoon perhaps imbrace the truth, if he were not courted with ſo many lyes, by deceivers that abound in the world. The common complaint and cry is, for the Religion that was in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time again. And that we have not now the ſame Religion. The Anſwer in brief is, that we have the ſame Religion ſtill, not a new. And that the true Proteſtant Religion which was then profeſt, is now, not altered, but ſettled, being reſtored to its priſtine purity, and purged from many abuſes wherewith it was but lately corrupted. As,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Many Popiſh and Arminian te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents were taught and publickly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that are contrary to the doctrine of our Church at firſt eſtabliſhed, as will appear by comparing them with the 39. Articles and the book of Homilies; the nine Articles of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writings of our former Biſhops.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:120048:77"/>
               <p>Secondly, Many Crucifixes, Images or Idols were ſet up in our moſt eminent Churches, and moſt eminent places of them; and that partly by connivence, partly by command of men, at that time of moſt eminent place and note, whereby Superſtition was nouriſhed, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try committed. But now theſe Images are contrary, 1. To the Word of God, expreſly forbidding them: 2. To the judgment of the ancient Chriſtians, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Councels, with great zeal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning them: And 3. of our own Church of <hi>England,</hi> as in the book of Homilies and 39. Articles may be ſeen.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Communion Table was altered both in name and place; from a Table to an Altar; from the body of the Church to the head or upper end of the Chancel, contrary to expreſs order ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t down in the book of Common Prayer, before the communion; where it is ſaid, that the Table ſhall ſtand in the body of the Church or in the Chancel, and the Prieſt ſhall ſtand at the north ſide; which he cannot do if he ſtand cloſe up to the wall: And if it might be placed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the diſcretion of the ordinary, yet
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:120048:78"/> he muſt have more diſcretion then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary that will make the end of a table the ſide, as one endeavored to do but that his Geometry failed him.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The Bowing uſed to the Communion Table, was a matter of worſe conſequence then was commonly imagined; It is the attendant on Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation and Conſubſtantiation; It ſerves to nouriſh thoſe Errours ſtill in mens minds; uſhers in many other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ſuperſtitions, and is the occaſion of groſs Idolatry.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The rails, wainſcot, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe courtains before the Table, as if it were the <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum</hi> of the Jews, or a Chappel intended for private Maſs; or as if none were holy enough to approach neer it but the Prieſt: alſo the Tapers, Copes, Veſtments, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things, lately uſed, though they ſeemed but ſmall matters to ſome, yet they were not the leſs dangerous for being little; for like little thieves they crept in at our Church windows to open doors to the great ones: and if theſe had continued, by this time they would have brought in the whole Maſs of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Idolatry; and thoſe that plead for
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:120048:78"/> them, are but the devils pimps that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the people, and under the name of things indifferent would lead them a whoring after Idolls.</p>
               <p>Hereunto we may add that horrible abuſe of Excommunication, the higheſt cenſure of the Church, that in the Courts Chriſtian was made a meſſenger to fetch in fees; and men were caſt out of the Church for not comming into the Court: to ſay no more. Laſtly, They err as much on the other hand, and are to be condemned, that ſcornfully or baſely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the Church and places ſet apart for the uſe of Gods Ordinances, which is ſeldom done but in open or ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the ordinances themſelves. Let them among other examples remember that of <hi>Julian</hi> unckle to the Apoſtate, who in contempt piſſed againſt the Communion Table: his bowels rotting out, he voyded his own excrements at his mouth. Our own times have not wanted like examples of mans impiety and Gods judgment. But leaving them to their naſty ſtables &amp;c. although we know God doth hear us in all places when we call upon him, yet that decent places be ſet apart and beautified with
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:120048:79"/> comely ornaments, is very fit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming ſuch holy duties and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices.</p>
               <p>There is one main rub yet that many ſtumble at, and that is the ſtrict exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of communicants, and ſuſpenſion upon ſome cauſes from the holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: to remove this, let them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it is no more but the duty of the Miniſter formerly enjoyned by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our own Church, as is to be ſeen in the book of Common Prayer: and therefore is no innovation.</p>
               <p>Theſe things and the like duly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we may ſee the Errour of many, who under the name of the Proteſtant Religion, do moſt of all oppoſe it: and think to eſtabliſh the Church of <hi>England</hi> with thoſe Engines that will utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it. Let all true-hearted Proteſtants conſider theſe things, and as they love the Church of <hi>England</hi> their Mother, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate her quarrel againſt thoſe that have ſo baſely abuſed her; thoſe crafty chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that under the name and authority of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> have cheated the people with thoſe counterfeit ſtuffs, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended but condemned.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:120048:79"/>
               <p>If there be any other alteration in our Church then what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th been mentioned, It is not of any ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ce, but ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance: there is no alteration in the body, but in the apparrel: An eminent Doctour of our own ſays (I am ſure no friend to Noveliſm) that Clerical habits &amp; veſtiments are not the body, but ſwadling clothes of Religion; and we know there is a time to leave off ſuch things. And ſo all other Ceremonies were judged altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by thoſe that firſt ordained them. As the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaid of his ſon, <hi>Scio me genuiſſe Mortalem;</hi> ſo they knew their decrees when they made them were not <hi>Median-Perſian</hi> Laws, but that they might and muſt be altered, if after times ſhould ſee as good reaſon to remove theſe Ceremonies, as they themſelves did to remove many before. <hi>See the Prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the book of Common-prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Biſhops are put down, and that is a great blot to the Reformation. But tell me, did ſtately Palaces, great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, and lordly titles, agree with the poverty, meekneſs, humility of our Saviour, whoſe ſervants they profeſs themſelves? And for a farther trial of the lawfulneſs of theſe things, a trial that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:120048:80"/> will not deceive. Let a form of prayer be drawn, and ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a complaint unto Almighty God fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſe things, and a ſupplication to reſtore them particularly, and by name, and let me ſee who dares go into the preſence of God with ſuch a prayer in his mouth? Things lawful and conſcionable we may with comfort pray for: but thoſe things that a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience dares not pray for, his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience condemns for unlawful.</p>
               <p>But the Church is trodden down, her lands and goods embeziled, &amp;c. that is the Biſhops Lands, &amp;c. ſtill a ſhrewd mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. If they are taken from them, and reſtored to the right owners, that every Church may have its proper maintenance, and they enjoy the means that take the pains; is this ſacriledg or Juſtice? And what was it when the Biſhops, &amp;c. held and enjoyed ſo many tithes and profits, properly belonging to other poor Miniſters, that were Church men, as well as themſelves, and took care of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? So much of their means as is not this way due to others, may well be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſettle a more uſeful Miniſtry, as the preſent neceſſities of the Church every where require.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:120048:80"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>Of Toleration.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough the Heathen had infinite Gods almoſt, and as many ſeveral Religions, Ceremonies, and forms of worſhip, yet we never read of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention among them about any difference of Religion; the Reaſon was, becauſe the Gods of the Heaven (as one ſays) were goods fellows, and content to ſhare that glory amongſt them, that was none of theirs; but the true God is a jealous God, and cannot endure a partner of that glory, that is properly his own. And therefore there can be no greater Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Sectaries, that they are not of God, then their great deſire of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of all Religions. But <hi>Joan. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lt.</hi> a ſmall <hi>Errour</hi> is ſharply taken up; it may warn us, not to ſuffer the leaſt <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> though not fundamental; for, tares, if ſuffered to grow, at laſt will pluck down the wheat. We muſt follow St. <hi>Pauls</hi> example, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.5. Who would not <hi>give place to falſe brethren, no not
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:120048:81"/> for an hour, that the truth of the Goſpel might continue.</hi> So we muſt not give place to any <hi>Errourist:</hi> But as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſays, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Their mouths muſt be ſtopt, becauſe their words eat like a canker.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17. And though ſmall at firſt, yet will eat out the very heart and life of all Religion at laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
